<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Salomon's pest-house, or tovver-royall. Newly re-edified and prepared to preserve Londoners with their families, and others, from the doubted deluge of the plague. Item, a laudable excercise [sic] for those that are departed, or shall depart out of the city into the country, to spend their time till they returne, a handfull of holy meditations usefull and requisite for Gods people, men and women, of all estates and degrees, in these doubtfull dayes, whether troubled in body or minde, and whether Gods visitation of the plague increase or decrease. / By the reverend, learned and godly divine I.D. preacher of Gods word. ; Whereunto is added Mr. Holland's admonition, and Mr. Phaer's prescription for bodily physicke. Also London looke-backe: a description or representation of the great and memorable mortality ann. 1625. in heroicke matchlesse lines,.</title>
            <author>I. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6176.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532321</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180761</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180761)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2133:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Salomon's pest-house, or tovver-royall. Newly re-edified and prepared to preserve Londoners with their families, and others, from the doubted deluge of the plague. Item, a laudable excercise [sic] for those that are departed, or shall depart out of the city into the country, to spend their time till they returne, a handfull of holy meditations usefull and requisite for Gods people, men and women, of all estates and degrees, in these doubtfull dayes, whether troubled in body or minde, and whether Gods visitation of the plague increase or decrease. / By the reverend, learned and godly divine I.D. preacher of Gods word. ; Whereunto is added Mr. Holland's admonition, and Mr. Phaer's prescription for bodily physicke. Also London looke-backe: a description or representation of the great and memorable mortality ann. 1625. in heroicke matchlesse lines,.</title>
                  <author>I. D.</author>
                  <author>Holland, Henry, 1583-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 69, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Holland.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴, A₁(contents, bound at end, rest of A lacking), B-K⁴ (last leaf blank?).</note>
                  <note>London look-backe. The description of the late great memorable and prodigious plague. 1625.--p. 56-69.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: [par.]₂, A₂₋₄ lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of London. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SALOMONS PEST-HOVSE, OR TOVVER-ROYALL.</p>
            <p>NEVVLY RE-EDIFIED and prepared to preſerve Londoners with their Families, and others, from the doubted Deluge of the Plague.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> A laudable excerciſe for thoſe that are departed, or ſhall depart out of the City into the Country, to ſpend their time till they returne,</p>
            <p>A handfull of Holy Meditations uſefull and requiſite for Gods people, men and women, of all Eſtates and degrees, in theſe doubtfull dayes, whether troubled in body or minde, and whether Gods Viſitation of the Plague increaſe or decreaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the reverend, learned and godly Divine</hi> I. D. <hi>Preacher of Gods Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hollands</hi> Admonition, and M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Phaers</hi> Preſcription for bodily Phyſicke.</p>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>London Looke-backe:</hi> A deſcription or repreſentation of the great and memorable Mortality <hi>Ann.</hi> 1625. in Heroicke matchleſſe lines,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for HENRY HOLLAND. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:2"/>
            <head>To the judicious Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued: The wiſeſt Preacher (of a mortall man, and of immortall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie,) that euer was or ſhall bee, inſpired with the ſpirit of God; ſaith, <hi>There is a time to weepe as well as to laugh, a time to mourne as well as to dance:</hi> And certes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery man and woman vnder their owne Vines and Fig-trees haue a long time ſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues with <hi>laughing</hi> and <hi>dauncing,</hi> or making merry with their friends; doubtleſſe now is the time that God calls for <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> at the leaſt: For, hath he not ſhot diuers of his Arrowes? and haue not ſome Bullets fallen from his warning Pieces? which Arrowes and Bullets, both poyſoned with the Peſtilence, haue hit and ſlaine ſome people not onely in and about this populous Citie, but elſewhere in the ſpatious Country alſo: And who perceiueth not that the deſtroying Angel hath vnſheathed his ſword and brandiſhed it ouer vs of this Citie, vs of this whole Land? Yea, the black Horſe of the Peſtilence with pale Death on his backe, hath beene and is, eft-ſoones, prauncing and trampling in the ſtreets of our Citie at midnight: And the Angell hauing wings hath flowne alſo into the Country, and there done as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Now, though the ſinfull ſonnes and daughters of
<pb facs="tcp:180761:3"/>
men lie, neuertheleſſe, ſtill ſleeping in their ſenſualites, yet the vigilant Watchmen of our Engliſh Iſrael haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouered both the one and the other: That is, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of the Goſpell obſeruing this Gods begun iudgement and further threat'ned puniſhment of the Peſtilence; they, I ſay, haue not ſpared both in Citie and Country, publickly, and priuately, with feruencie to pray for vs, for the preuenting and diuerting of Gods further furious Hand vpon vs, and in their preachings with their ſiluer Trumpets to lift vp their voyces to ſound aloud; and cry downe the high-crying ſinnes of this Citie, of this Land: Yea, diuers of theſe worthy Miniſters haue beene and are ſo zealous in praying and preaching for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Perſeuerance, that their throats are growne hoarſe, their bodies weak, and their healths impaired: In ſo much that vulgar Profaniſts and Carnalliſts of the (like as <hi>Feſtus</hi> once ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi>) are ready to ſay, <hi>much zeale hath made them mad:</hi> But howeuer, for this their aſsiduitie and indefatigable <hi>labour of loue</hi> their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with the Lord; and though <hi>the zeale of Gods Houſe doe eat them vp;</hi> yet <hi>they ſhall</hi> once <hi>ſhine as Starres in the Firmament of Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among thoſe reuerend Diuines, one hath compiled this comfortable Treatiſe, or to vſe its proper Title-pharſe, hath reedified and prepared this <hi>Peſt-houſe,</hi> or <hi>Tower-Royall,</hi> firſt built by King <hi>Salomon</hi> ſo many hundred yeeres agone, &amp; before he turned from a Prince to a Preacher.</p>
            <p>If any liſt to be curiouſly, inquiſitiue and aske, who or what is the Authour, this <hi>I.D?</hi> or to queſtion his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of reuerend, learned, godly, Giue me the publiſher his friend leaue to anſwer; Firſt, that happ'ly his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb facs="tcp:180761:3"/>
is ſuch and for ſome reaſons in his Chriſtian wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome he deſires not to haue the Phylacterie of his Name expreſſed: and it being ſo, he is not the firſt of Gods people that hath deſired his name to be obſcured in a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vſefull worke: Secondly, for his attributes, let me alſo anſwer; for the firſt, they that know him, doe know him ſo to be; for the two latter, let his labour it ſelfe anſwer and witneſſe for him.</p>
            <p>To conclude; Whoſoeuer the Author is or whatſoeuer I the publiſher am, Know this, courteous Reader, that it was written and is publiſhed for mine owne and thy Chriſtian ſolace and comfort, now in a requiſite time of a begun Sickneſſe and Mortalitie: the meditation wherof in our beſt healths; will doe vs, doubtleſſe, no hurt: And who knoweth? Yes, the Lord knoweth whether it may be his <hi>Swan-like Song,</hi> this writing <hi>mine.</hi> For who can number vnto himſelfe any more dayes or houers? <hi>Lord teach me ſo to number my dayes, that I may apply my heart to wiſedome;</hi> in labouring to make my peace with God. And for my paines in publiſhing hereof, let me craue your Prayers. And ſo I betake you to God and the good Word of his Grace, which is able (in ſickneſſe &amp; in health; in life &amp; in death, in Citie or Countrie,) to build you vp further, and to giue you an Inheritance (in <hi>Salomons</hi> ſtrong <hi>Towre-Royall)</hi> among them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Farewell in Chriſt. <hi>H.D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:4"/>
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript to the Reader.</head>
            <p>SInce God began this yeere, his Viſitation, and to ſhake his Rod of the Peſtilence ouer vs, I haue obſerued an errour among the ſonnes of men, <hi>viz.</hi> They haue beene and are very diligent in enquiring after the weekly Bils of mortality, and they that could firſt obtaine the Bill from their Pariſh Clarks, haue acknowledged to be moſt beholden vnto them: and I will not ſimply condemne this their diligence: But come we to enquire what vſe they haue made of this their double diligence and prime-intelligence: If they haue found an <hi>increaſe</hi> of the number, haue they humbled themſelues in Prayer, endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to depart from their ſinnes, &amp; to trauaile to this Towre-Royall, in the ſequell, for ſafetie? Surely no, few or none haue ſo done: the <hi>increaſe</hi> happ'ly hath deiected them, made them murmure, and proiect to flee to their Country-houſes here or there, and peraduenture to ſend beforehand their Wiues, Children, and Houſhold-ſtuffe: yea, very carefull they haue been, &amp; are for this their bodily ſafegard. Againe, on the other ſide, if they haue ſeene by the Bill a <hi>decreaſe</hi> in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; how many, nay how few haue returned to God by the way of thankfulneſſe for ſuch his great mercy &amp; forbearance? I feare, and it appeares, that rather they haue beene thereby encouraged to goe on in ſecurity, if not in ſenſualitie. I may ſay therefore with the Authour and Founder of our Towre-Royall. <hi>This is (alſo) an euill vnder the Sun,</hi> committed by the ſonnes of men; Of whom I my ſelfe being one, &amp; ingenuouſly confeſſing, I cannot free my ſelfe from being tainted with the Infection of this <hi>euill,</hi> will ſay no more: but doe humbly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore for my ſelfe, and all the Iſrael of God, more wiſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, contrite and thankefull hearts, in obſeruing his workes. <hi>Open thou my lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.15. Pſal. 119.18.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, that my mouth may ſhew forth thy praiſe.</hi> And <hi>open mine eyes that I may ſee the wonders of thy workes.</hi> Iterum in Chriſto vale.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:4"/>
            <head>SALOMONS PEST-HOVSE <hi>OR</hi> TOWRE-ROYALL,</head>
            <head type="sub">Collected out of the 18. Chapter of the Prouerbs, verſe 10.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong towre: the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous runneth vnto it, and is preſerued.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head type="sub">Confirmed by the practiſe of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. Chron. Chap. 21. ver. 17. and 26.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>And he called vpon the Lord, and he anſwered him by fire from heauen.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He whole Colledge of the bodily Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and the Prince of them, that wiſe and learned <hi>Galen,</hi> preſcibe for the time of Plague, that of all reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to preuent the contagion, the beſt is, to flie &amp; ſhun the infected and corrupted ayre, and to depart vnto a wholeſome and purer ayre: and that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180761:5"/>
with theſe three rules, <hi>Citò, longè, tardè.</hi> Depart ſpeedily, farre off, and returne ſlowly. As this is Phyſically preſcribed, ſo it is diligently practiſed, as daily experience teacheth, of all ſorts of men, yea of the Phyſicians themſelues; I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Phyſician, nor diſprooue the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of the ſons of men, if they vſe departure lawfully, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not ſinning, <hi>Contra Patriam, charitatem, vocationem,</hi>) againſt their Country, their calling, &amp; Chriſtian charity. But becauſe by the corruption of our nature (which is more than the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the ayre) we ſuffer our ſelues as with maine ſayle to be carried away from the Creatour to the creatures; fixing all our ſenſes more vpon the aerial corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than vpon the inward cauſe of the contagion, the rottenneſſe of our bones, which we carrie within our ſelues, &amp; are more carefull to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part into the Countrey than vnto the Lord; as if by the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our feet we could out-runne <hi>Him</hi> who rideth vpon the wings of the Cherubims,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4.</note> which cauſeth that the Lord hath a Purſiuant, which he ſendeth to arreſt ſome in the pure ayre, (namely the Plague it ſelfe) which hath arreſted ſome in the Countrie as well as the Citie,<note place="margin">Anno. 1603. and 1625.</note> as the experience of the two laſt Viſitations verified and this preſent yeere haue ſhewen vnto vs all, verifing the threatning of the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.22. This is the reaſon why the whole Colledge of the ſpirituall Phyſicians of our ſoules haue preſcribed for the time of Plague, a better flight and departure, than that which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Galen</hi> and the reſt; namely (to the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi>) by the feet of Prayer, mentioned and ſtoried by that wiſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in the words prefixed. And as it is preſcribed, ſo it hath been practiſed of the Saints of God: among the reſt, of King <hi>Dauid</hi> in the time of Plague, as the ſecond place adioyning vnto the firſt doth witneſſe. Of this place then, which is the right Arke, &amp; the little <hi>Zoar,</hi> whereunto our firſt care ought to be in the time of plague to depart, and which is alſo the truſtie friend and ſeruant to aide the ſicke, and the Exerciſe for them that are departed, to ſpend the time till they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, giue me leaue Chriſtian Readers to diſcourſe out of the harmonie of theſe two places here prefixed.</p>
            <p>To pray well, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> is an excellent art, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180761:5"/>
doth adorne a Chriſtian, but it is not ſufficient to know that we muſt pray, but alſo in what manner: and therfore that we might the better be inſtructed in the going to this place, and become skilfull in this art, I will braunch the deſcription of this place in theſe three ſeuerall parts, which will ſtore vs with a cluſter of ſingular Meditations.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the name of the place, it is <hi>(the name of the Lord.)</hi> The ſecond is, the qualitie, condition, propertie; and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, expreſſed in two things; Firſt, becauſe it is <hi>(a ſtrong towre)</hi> ſecondly, by the ſucceſſe of thoſe that run vnto it (and it <hi>exalted</hi>) or deliuered: which is the thing which they receiue that run to it.</p>
            <p>The third thing is, what maner of perſons they muſt be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that flie to it, &amp; what houſehould ſtuffe they muſt carrie thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them to be receiued, noted in theſe words <hi>(the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous runneth vnto it.)</hi> As for the place, let me obſerue foure things. For as in the time of Plague, for our departure, firſt it is neceſſarie, that we know the name of the place whereunto we go: ſecondly, that we haue feet to beare &amp; carie vs thither: thirdly, that wee haue a direction that wee might not erre: fourthly, that we haue ſome right and intereſt there, or ſome acquaintance, that we may be receiued. So likewiſe theſe foure things are neceſſarie to be knowne of vs, in our ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all departure.</p>
            <p>Touching the name of the place whereunto <hi>Dauid</hi> fled in the time of plague, as it hath diuers names,<note place="margin">1 The name of the place.</note> ſo in this place it is called the name of <hi>Iehouah.</hi> Heere I pretermit the fiue ſeueral ſignifications of the name of the Lord vſed in the booke of God, taking it in this place, firſt for the Lord himſelf ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for his attributes by which he doth manifeſt himſelfe. Of which <hi>Moſes, Num.</hi> 14. bringeth in a perfect catalogue, &amp; the Lord hath deliuered this his name by proclamation, <hi>Exo.</hi> 34.5.6. <hi>The Lord, the Lord ſtrong, mercifull, and gratious, ſlow to anger, and aboundant in goodnes and truth, &amp;c.</hi> God then the <hi>almightie, eternall, immortall, inuiſible Lord, the iudge of the world,</hi> Pſal. 94.2. <hi>God, mercifull and gratious,</hi> the ſupreme Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of our ſoules, <hi>who healeth all our iniquities.</hi> Pſal. 103 <hi>God to whom power belongeth, and whoſe is ſaluation alone,</hi> Pſal. 62. is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180761:6"/>
the place it ſelfe wherunto <hi>Dauid,</hi> and wee ought to flie from the contagion. The name of a place if it be knowne, famous and renowned, hath often much force to perſwade vs rather to goe vnto ſuch a place, than vnto ſuch or ſuch: ſurely there was neuer name of place more worthy to goe vnto, then the name of <hi>Iehouah.</hi> O yee righteous ſoules that thirſt or may thirſt by reaſon of the heat of the plague vpon your beddes, flie vnto this place, to the waters of comfort: here are wels enough to be drawne at: this is the name which God hath proclaimed to the world, and whereby he would be knowne so men, that if euer they come to him, they may ſpeake their mindes in the confidence and truſt of this amiable name. Eſteeme it not ſtrange, beloued, that the name of a place is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to the Lord: for that hee is a place of refuge, three things are able to prooue: Firſt the witnes of God himſelfe: ſecond, the confeſſion of the righteous: third, the word <hi>(run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning)</hi> here vſed by king <hi>Salomon.</hi> As for the Lord he doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute vnto himſelf this name by the pen of the holy Ghoſt, calling himſelfe <hi>a ſecret place,</hi> Pſal. 91.1. <hi>a throne of Grace,</hi> Heb. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 4.16. <hi>a refuge,</hi> Pſal. 9 9. <hi>a fortreſſe,</hi> Pſal. 18.2. <hi>a ſtrong tower,</hi> and ſuch like more. Secondly this is the confeſſion of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Of <hi>Dauid</hi> the father in diuers places, Pſal. 18.2. <hi>The Lord is my fortreſſe and my refuge:</hi> and in the 32.7. <hi>Thou art my ſecret place, and compaſſeſt me about with ioyfull deliuerance:</hi> and ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.22. This is alſo the confeſſion of the ſonne in this place: and of all the Saints of God, vnto whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions I referre you, as they are ſet down by the holy Ghoſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in the booke of God. Thirdly, the word <hi>(runneth)</hi> implieth as much, which giueth me entrance to the ſecond point, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto vs the feet which we need, to goe vnto this place, the which if ye are deſirous to know,<note place="margin">The feet to carry vs thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> they are two in number (Faith and Praier). Faith the firſt, for if by faith we ſtand, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 24. by faith we may alſo goe to the Lord who is faithfull. Now how could we goe vnto him by the feete of prayer, if wee did not beleeue in him? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. The ſecond, is prayer, a ſpirituall legge to beare vs thither, noted by <hi>Salomon,</hi> making mention of <hi>running:</hi> by <hi>Ionah,</hi> ſpeaking of comming. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>And my prayer came vnto thee, in thine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180761:6"/>
holy temple?</hi> By the Apoſtle, when he ſpeaketh of going, <hi>let vs</hi> therefore goe vnto the throne of grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. Laſtly, by the holy Ghoſt, vſing this word <hi>Climbing. Apoc.</hi> 8.4. Both the name of the place which is appointed for vs to goe vnto, and the ſpirituall legs which the Lord hath giuen vs to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vs thither, doe preach vnto the ſonnes of men the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodnes &amp; mercy of the Lord toward them. In this world we are as pilgrims, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>hauing here no continuing Citie, Heb.</hi> 13.14 and while we are at home in the body, wee are abſent from the Lord, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. In which pilgrimage, <hi>Many are the troubles of the righteous, Pſal.</hi> 34. O the great goodnes of the Lord then, that hee hath giuen vs feete to come vnto him, and made himſefe a place of refuge for vs in all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles! which goodneſſe is comfortable vnto the faithfull: for as it is a comfort vnto the pilgrim, ſhepheard, or ſouldier, to haue in the heate of the day a place of refuge to refreſh their wearied members: So likewiſe what a comfort is it for you O afflicted ſoules in the heat of your afflictions, to haue the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> for a ſacred Sanctuarie! the Lord is not like vnto the Princes of the earth, who deſire not to be moleſted with the requeſts of their diſtreſſed ſubiects. It is a ioy to the wearied ſtudent, that he may ſometime come home to his fathers houſe &amp; recreate himſelfe: Into this world the Lord hath ſent vs as in an Vniuerſitie, which although it is farre off from our fathers houſe, yet the Lord hath giuen vs ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall feet, by which in a moment wee can aſcend vnto our fathers houſe, and recreate there our wearied ſpirits. This world is a waſte deſart, if wee neede any thing, here are the legges by which ſpeedily we may runne to this place, and prouide our ſelues. If the Lord hath caſt vs downe vpon our beds, and that wee cannot vſe the feet of our bodies, behold, he hath giuen vs other feet, to vſe in ſtead of theſe. King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> viſited with the plague, could not vſe the feet of the fleſh, but with the feet of the ſpirit, went vnto this place, known vnto him by the name of <hi>Iehouah Ionah</hi> is locked vp in a priſon, in the belly of the Whale, (the Lords priſon) and cannot ſtirre himſelfe, and yet by the vertue of theſe feet, out of the depth he aſcendeth to the holy temple of <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180761:7"/>
               <note place="margin">The hoſe to put on.</note>Now that theſe feet may be able to beare vs thither, and that they may not faile vs in our voyage, they muſt put on the hoſe of faith: and as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>our feet muſt be ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace.</hi> And as the feet to that Image of <hi>Daniel were part of yron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph 6 15.</note> 
               <hi>part of clay,</hi> which the Prophet expoundeth partly ſtrong, partly weake or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken:<note place="margin">Dan 2 42.</note> So the feet of our prayers are, according to the hoſen wherewith they are couered; if they put on feare and diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, they will be ſhiuering and ſinking downeward, <hi>of clay,</hi> weake, and impotent; if they put on faith and confidence in the mercies of God, they will be feet <hi>of yron,</hi> ſtrong, ſtable and firme, keeping vs vpright, and will carrie vs to the very throne of grace.<note place="margin">A dirction to know the way.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Further, as they that depart into the Countrey, if they know not the way to the place whereunto they goe, muſt haue a guide, or a direction, becauſe they ſhould not erre; So in the going to this place, becauſe there are ſo many falſe guides and directions, the Lord himſelfe hath giuen vs a Card of direction to lead vs thereunto, the witneſſe of his holy word, written and ſealed, that can neuer deceiue vs. As the fierie pillar in the deſart, ſhewed the way vnto the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites: So this word of the Lord is a fierie pillar vnto vs in the darke deſart of this world, to ſhew vs the way to that heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Canaan; it is the <hi>lanthorne vnto our feete, and a light to our pathes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. and therefore, according to the direction of our Sauiour, <hi>Let our loynes be girded, and let vs beare in our hands this ſhining light.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 The right or intereſt which the faithfull haue to this place.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, to go to this place, it is neceſſarie to know what right or intereſt we haue in it. In the places whereunto men betake their ſelues in the time of plague, either they haue ſome right or intereſt there, becauſe they are their owne, or becauſe they haue ſome friends or acquaintance there that will receiue them; or laſtly, becauſe they haue either hired or purchaſed a houſe. So likewiſe vnto the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> the place where we ought to goe in the time of plague, as alſo at all other times, we haue a ſpeciall right and intereſt. Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe it is our owne, for he is our God and our Lord, not by nature, but by gift and donation: Secondly, there we haue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180761:7"/>
acquaintance and our beſtfriends; God our father, Chriſt our brother, the holy Ghoſt our comforter. Thirdly, becauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we haue purchaſed it; not we our ſelues, by corruptible gold, or by our merites, but Chriſt for vs by his precious blood, hath obtained this place of refuge for vs in our troubles. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.17. in his prayer, ſheweth vpon what right and encouragement in the time of plague he went to this place, <hi>(O Lord my God I beſeech thee, &amp;c.)</hi> it was then, becauſe the Lord was his God; he had a particular feeling of the loue of God toward him, and knew him to be his God for hee had had ſome experience of deliuerance. The reaſon why we muſt haue this right, is becauſe being infected with the plague of ſinne, we ſhould not be receiued. In the Countrie, they will not receiue thoſe that are infected with the plague: Neither can they alſo, in whoſe ſoules the plague of ſin doth reigne, be admitted to this place, and therefore the Lord hath giuen vs Chriſt the righteous, to couer our vnrighteouſneſſe, that thus as pure &amp; cleane we might come vnto him. I know by mine experience, that in the Country heretofore, they would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dmit ſome that came from the Citie, vnleſſe they had put on new apparrell. To come vnto that heauenly Ieruſalem by the feet of prayer, we cannot be admitted,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.24.</note> except we put off the old man, and put on the new man which is created in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and therfore, that we ſhould not be hindered to go thither, <hi>He hath put on vs, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 13.14. that being adorned with his righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, as <hi>Iacob</hi> was with the garment of his brother <hi>Eſau, We might with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence approach to the throne of grace, Heb.</hi> 4. It is only then in the name of Chriſt that we muſt goe to the name of <hi>Iehouah, Ioh.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 57. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16 14. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1. In his name, the poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> hath as much right to go vnto it, as king <hi>Salomon:</hi> the infected as the ſound: the learned as the vnlearned: for Chriſt prayeth for them all: &amp; as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Chriſt prayeth with vs all as our brother; he prayeth in vs all as our head, he is prayed vnto by vs all, as our Lord, but he prayeth for vs all, as our high Prieſt.</hi> Let then the Romaniſts in the time of plague, run vnto the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> in the name of Saint <hi>Sebaſtian;</hi> Alas, they ſhall not be admitted: for Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180761:8"/>
alone, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>is the eye wherewith wee ſee the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the hand to offer vp our prayers, and the mouth to ſpeake vnto him.</hi> But as for vs, with <hi>Dauid</hi> let vs goe vnto him by force of this right, ſaying with him, <hi>O Lord our God, we beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The practiſe of King Dauid.</note>Hauing vnderſtood the name of the place, with other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, let vs now examine the practiſe of King <hi>Dauid;</hi> vnto this place, with theſe feete, by the ſame right, following the true direction, hee runned in the time of the plague with his family, the Elders of Iſrael. For he fled not to his Caſtle, neither departed he cut of Iewrie, nor tranſported his family into another place, but as it is ſtoried, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.26. <hi>(He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Lord.)</hi> Here is a foundation whereupon ſome prodigall of their liues, vncharitable to others, proude in their conceites, build the vnlawfulneſſe of departing out of the contagious places in the time of plague, condemning it by the example of King <hi>Dauid</hi> in generall,<note place="margin">Obiection.</note> without any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in all manner of perſons, which their vncharitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit I will not heere refute, I referre the Reader to that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Treatiſe of that reuerend father, <hi>Theodorus Beza,</hi> written touching this matter, wherein he learnedly, ſoundly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly refuteth their groſſe opinion; onely let me deſtroy their building which they erect vpon the example of King <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwere:</note> Foure particulars can hinder them to make a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> concluſion out of this example. Firſt, the ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that plague, for the ſpace of three dayes, or of a halfe of a day, as ſome of the learned are of opinion; whoſe reaſons I will not alleage, which left him no time to deliberate vpon departure. Secondly, the generalitie of the Peſtilence, being ſpred from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſhebah,</hi> which left him no place free to go vnto: for whither ſhould he flie, ſeeing that the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> was ſpread all ouer the land? 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. Thirdly, his owne guiltineſſe, that plague being cauſed by his ſinne, the numbring of the people, which cauſed ſuch a ſorrow in <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he was ready by his owne death to redeeme the publike calamitie, praying vnto the Lord, 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.17. <hi>O Lord my God I beſeech thee, let thine hand be on me, and on my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> houſe, and not on thy people for their deſtruction.</hi> Fourthly, the ſoundneſſe of Ieruſalem, the place where he was, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180761:8"/>
Angel hauing not yet, or very ſparingly touched the head Citie, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.15. the Lord repenting of the euill, when the Angel came to Ieruſalem: theſe foure particulars are able to caſt downe their building, and to diſprooue their conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: <hi>Dauid</hi> fled not, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is vnlawfull for any man to depart: the true conſequence, if we would argue out of this place, might be this: <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; the Elders departed not: <hi>Ergo,</hi> let not Magiſtrate forſake his Citie, nor the Miniſter his flocke. Hauing pluckt out the weedes and the thiſtles, let vs as the good husbandman ſow the good ſeede. As this then prooueth not the vnlawfulneſſe of departure; ſo on the other ſide, it doth commend vnto vs king <hi>Dauids</hi> praying,<note place="margin">The true vſe of the example</note> and his ſpirituall departure, teaching vs that in the time of plague, our firſt and principall care ought to bee, as well before our departure, as in our departure if we are ſo minded, (for I vrge no neceſſitie of it) to flie and runne by the feete of faith and prayer to the name of the Lord, which being forgotten, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or negligently practiſed, maketh our departure vnlawful. Imitate the King then, O ye righteous ſoules, in this threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned tempeſt of the plague, let your ſoules take (the wings of a Doue) the motion and agility of the ſpirit of God, and let them flie by the ſtrength of their prayers to the boſome of Gods mercies where they ſhall be at reſt. <hi>Dauid</hi> in this his going to the name of the Lord, hath ſhowen and manifeſted foure things: His Conſcience, Humilitie, Memory, Wiſedome. His Conſcience, that it was good: his Humilitie, great: his Memorie, holy: his Wiſedome, right.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt, the ſpirit of prayer is a ſigne of a good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Conſcience; for as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Lib. de caſt. Oratio de conſcientia procedit ſi conſcientia erubaeſcat, erubeſcet oratio. Prayer doth proceede from the Conſcience: if the Conſcience bluſh, prayer will alſo be aſhamed.</hi> O it is an excellent thing that we can giue our ſelues to this holy exerciſe: let one haue riches, honour, pleaſures, let him be adored as a little god, if he haue not the ſpirit of prayer to puſh him forward with <hi>Dauid,</hi> in the midſt of his felicitie, he is moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his miſerie and humilitie, for a King is become <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180761:9"/>
a begger, and at the gate of the King of heauen he vſeth ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of ſubmiſſion. <hi>(I beſeech thee O Lord)</hi> Loe here O proud ſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> of thy ſelfe thou haſt nothing, but like a poore ſuppliant begger thou art conſtrained to goe before the gate of that right God, aſwel the king that fitteth vpon his throne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> that ſitteth before the doore of the rich man. Thirdly his memory, the ſubiect wherof was the Lord, O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembrance! Although he had as it were forgotten him by his ſinne in his proſperitie, yet he remembreth him by his praier in his affliction: O the excellencie of praier, it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of our beſt friend, whoſe remembrance is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our diſtreſſed ſoules. The ſubiect of our memoris, haue beene along time commodities, pleaſures, riches, honor, triumphs, &amp; therfore, ô England, behold another ſubiect to exerciſe the art of thy memory: If then we haue forgotten him by our feruent prayer in our ſin, let vs now remember him by our feruent praier in our affliction. Many haue practiſed the art of memorie, according to the memoratiue Art, and precepts of memorie, which appoint places, and their furniture, for the helpe of ſuch as are vnexperienced; but let vs practiſe the art of this holy memorie, let God be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the ſubiect, &amp; in this our afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let theſe be our helpes: Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> let vs remember in our praier the commandement of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. Secondly the name of him, whom we call vpon, that it is <hi>Iehouah,</hi> Lord, our God, a God not in ſhew, but in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and performance: a ſtrong God, a towre of defence, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they that know this name wil truſt in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what he is by nature, how ſweet and amiable, how rich in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> mercie, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. Fourthly, what he is by promiſe, how faithfull <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and true, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. Laſtly, what he is by couenant, made vnto <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, not in the blood of bulles, but in the bloud of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Further <hi>Dauid</hi> hath ſhewen his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; that in the choice of the place, taking his marke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and directing his petition to the true and proper peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ode. Imitate the wiſdom of king <hi>Dauid</hi> in his choice, he that goeth to a place, runneth aright and wiſely, if he be wiſe, and not by crooked and erroneous waies: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſheweth vs the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180761:9"/>
right way, for to what place ſhould we goe but to this, when our ſorrowes are multiplied? ſhall we follow the waies of the wicked, and ſay with them, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. <hi>It is in vaine, that I haue ſerued him, and what profit is it, that I haue kept his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> Or ſhall we runne vpon the way of impatience, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding griefe to griefe, liuing the life of <hi>Caine,</hi> or dying the death of <hi>Iudas,</hi> drowning our ſoules in a gulfe of deſperation Shall we ſpend the time in bannings, execrations, curſing the day and night, the earth that beareth vs, the ayre that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpireth vs? Not ſo, O Chriſtian ſoules, call vpon the name of the Lord with <hi>Dauid,</hi> there was neuer name ſo worthie to be called vpon, in heauen or earth, ſo mightie for deliuerance, ſo ſure for protection, ſo gainefull for ſucceſſe, ſo compendious to cut off vnneceſſarie labours as the name of <hi>Iehouah:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hauing vnderſtood the Conſcience, Humilitie, Memorie,<note place="margin">6. The cauſes to mooue vs to goe to this place.</note> and Wiſedome of <hi>Dauid;</hi> let me open to you the reaſons to mooue &amp; perſwade vs to go to this place. Fiue things mooue the ſons of men in the time of plague to depart from conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious places, vnto a purer ayre. Firſt, the counſel of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Secondly, the practiſe of others. Thirdly, the danger or perill which they are like to fall in. Fourthly, deſire of health and life. Fifthly, the experience of ſucceſſe. Let the ſame be motiues vnto vs in this infection, to perſwade vs to run ſpeedily vnto this Arke of <hi>Noah.</hi> Firſt, it is preſcribed by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1:"/> the whole Colledge of the ſpirituall Phyſicians, by God the father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician; by God the ſon, who preſcribing the remedies which men ought to vſe in the laſt dayes, in which the Trinitie of puniſhments, Famine,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Warres, and Peſtilence ſhould reigne, giueth this counſell, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36, <hi>Watch and pray continually;</hi> by Prophets, Apoſtles, &amp; wiſe men, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 38.9. and 17.23. Secondly, the practiſe of the ſpirituall Phyſicians, as they haue preſcribed it, ſo they haue alſo practiſed it, &amp; haue fled vnto this place; to this Sanctuarie went the renowmed Patriarkes, the godly Princes, the holy Prophets, the bleſſed Apoſtles, the Prince of glory, the ſon of the immortal God, the conſtant Martyrs: whoſe examples ye ſhall find in the ſtore-houſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180761:10"/>
The example of the bodily Phyſicians, of which ſome depart in the time of plague, hath much force to make vs haſten our departure; how much more ought the practiſe of the ſpiritual Phyſicians ſpurre vs forward vpon our ſpirituall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> voyage. Thirdly, the danger, which is threefold, <hi>(In nobis, circa nos, contra nos)</hi> In vs, round about vs, againſt vs. In vs the plague of ſin: round about vs, the fire of the preſent plague: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, Sathan who ſeeketh to make vs curſe the Lord, and the fire of Gods wrath and anger: To auoid this threefold <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4:"/> danger, run to the Towre and to this bleſſed Zoar. The fourth motiue, is the deſire of life and health; we need at this time a double health, the health of the ſoule and body: let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>goe boldly vnto the throne of grace, that we may receiue mercy, and find grace to helpe in time of need, Heb.</hi> 4.16. Why went that woman which was diſeaſed with an iſſue of blood twelue yeares vnto Chriſt, but that ſhe might receiue her health:<note place="margin">Matth. 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. The ſickneſſe of the plague is an iſſue of blood, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once opened, will euer run, and keepe a courſe if it be not ſtanched by the power and mercie of God: which mercie is onely obtained, by going vnto his ſacred name: to obtaine this double health, <hi>Dauid</hi> went vnto this place, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. that the plague of his ſoule might be healed, and the bodily plague be remooued. If we are as it were dead for ſorrow, prayer will reuiue vs, for it is, <hi>Vita animae,</hi> the life of the ſoule: &amp; as <hi>Chryſ</hi> termeth it, <hi>Eſt anima ipſius animae, It is the ſoule of the ſoule.</hi> If we goe into the Countrey which cannot ſaue vs; how much more ought we to flie to this name, which hath the power to do it: this his power, being accompanied with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and kindneſſe, for thou O Lord, art good and gracious, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and of great compaſſion. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8 6. Fiftly, experience of good ſucceſſe, is the laſt motiue, they which haue fled to this place, haue not beene ſtopped by the way, but haue had good ſpeede. Goe vnto King <hi>Hezekiah, Iob, Dauid,</hi> and the reſt, and they will preach vnto you by experience, the experience <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of this ſucceſſe. This ſucceſſe is grounded vpon three things, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as vpon three firme pillars, the Power, the Will and Promiſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Goodneſſe and mercie of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:180761:10"/>His power, <hi>I haue heard it that power belongeth vnto God, Pſal.</hi> 62.11. There was neuer affliction or ſore ſo great, but the hand of that Phyſician hath beene able to maſter it, the leaſt finger of his right hand being of more puiſſance, then the whole arme of fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His will and promiſe, Pſal.</hi> 91.1. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.32. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Eccle.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 31.9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.13. The King of heauen is not like vnto the Princes of the earth, or vnto that <hi>Philip</hi> of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, who anſwered vnto the widow comming in his Court to him, to be heard, I am not at leiſure, (vnto which alſo ſhee anſwered iuſtly, then be not a King any longer) for ſeeing that he hath promiſed it, he is alſo willing, his promiſe being ſigned with the finger of the holy Ghoſt, and ſealed with the blood of his beloued and annoynted. Neither is he like vnto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. who anſwered, trouble me not, my doores are ſhut; the gate of heauen is alwayes open for vs. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh not his promiſe as King <hi>Salomon.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.20.21.23. <hi>Aske my mother, for I will not ſay thee nay;</hi> and yet behold how this time is changed, <hi>Adoniah</hi> hath ſpoken this word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne life; of the Lords promiſe wee need not doubt, but with <hi>Dauid</hi> boldly we may ſpeake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.7. <hi>In the day of my trouble I will call vpon thee, for thou wilt heare me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>His goodneſſe, mercie, and liberalitie, which is ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> great that he giueth meat to the yong rauens which call vpon him, Pſal.</hi> 147.9. Doubt not then, but that hee will heare the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of men, whom he hath made a little lower then the Angels, to crowne them with glorie aboue other creatures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.56. Let therefore, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, thy prayer aſcend, and Gods mercie will deſcend,</hi> ſhall wee diſtruſt his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>who is rich to all that call vpon him? Rom.</hi> 10.12. Or ſhall we ſuſpect his bountifulneſſe, which <hi>powreth out plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully his bleſsings vpon all fleſh? Rom.</hi> 8.32. And although we haue offended him, yet our offences will not ſtop his mercies. Men, when they haue done any good turne to any, if they bee neuer ſo little offended, they caſt men in the teeth with the benefits they haue done them, and vpbraid them with the good turnes they haue ſhewed; wherefore men are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180761:11"/>
loath to make requeſt to ſuch for any thing: If wee goe vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Iam 1.5.</note> we ſhal not meete with one that is of ſuch a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and nature: he, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, reproacheth no man; nor keepeth his anger for euer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.9. The wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe, mercie, and goodneſſe of the Prince to haue vs, maketh vs alſo willing to goe to him; who more willing, then he that is our Father, our Sauiour, then he that hath ſuffered for vs, ſcoffings, ſpittings, bands, ſtripes, and death it ſelfe? Neuer lap of the mother hath beene ſo open to her babes, as the bowels of Gods compaſſions are open to the righteous. Harken to this, yee faint ſpirits, be ſtrengthened yee weake hands and feeble knees, receiue this comfort, that he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, he doth deliuer, hee yet will and can deliuer. I ende this point with the 13.14. and 15. verſes of the 10. Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romanes: wherein behold a ſingular and compendious gradation. As they that would come to King <hi>Salomon</hi> ſitting vpon his throne, were faine to runne vp ſixe ſtaires (for his throne, was mounted vnto by ſixe ſtaires) ſo the perfection and conſummation of man going to the throne of the true <hi>Salomon</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, aſcendeth and ariſeth by ſixe degrees: the higheſt and the happieſt ſtaires being, inuocating and ſauing, prayer and deliuerance. Theſe are then the fiue reaſons, by which wiſe Chriſtians ought to be guided. I imitate King <hi>Dauid,</hi> only reſorting to the wings of the Lords fauour. And herein we ſhould be wiſe, if we leuel our hearts and affections at the very right center and marke of prayer (which is the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> alone) and the period or ſcope in whom our requeſts muſt end.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fiue ſorts of men erring in the going to this place.</note>But alas, there are fiue ſortes of men, which make choice of other places, reiecting the wiſedome of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the ſpirituall Phyſicians, and the practiſe to the Saints of God, going a crooked, a circular, and endleſſe way, not towards the marke, nor with a right foot as the Apoſtle <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſpeaketh <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. The firſt kind, flie firſt to the helpe of mortall man, and with <hi>Aſa</hi> make ſpeed to the bodily Phyſician, to the confections of Arte, or to the purer ayre, not once mindfull of this place; but when all helpes faile them, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180761:11"/>
that the Lord ſendeth his Sergiant and heauenly Purſiphant to arreſt them, then they returne to runne to this place. What name ſhall we giue you (O yee of little faith) but the name of weake Chriſtians? Put not your truſt in the ſonne of man, for there is no helpe in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146. There is a ſecond <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſort, which runne onely to the ordinarie creatures, deriding the name <hi>Iehouah,</hi> yea denying that there euer hath beene, or is yet at this preſent, ſuch a place to be found, whereunto the righteous is preſerued, ſuch as <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribeth in the 10. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 3.4. <hi>Which ſeeke not God, but contemne him, and thinke they ſhall neuer be mooued.</hi> O yee meere Atheiſts, what name deſerue you, but that name, which the Lord himſelfe giueth you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. the name of fooles? If <hi>Cain</hi> hath beene reicted, becauſe hee offered an vnworthie ſacrifice, what deſerue they that offer none at all? The third ſort runne to a place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> whoſe name is Hell, ſeeking to Sathan and his artes, gadding to the woman of Endor, or to the Idoll of Ekron, as <hi>Saul,</hi> as <hi>Nero,</hi> as <hi>Iulian:</hi> Returne, returne, O yee wretched and bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſonnes of men, with the name of deuilliſh idolaters. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fourth ſort, ſeeketh to dwell vnder the protection and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their merites and good workes: but theſe alas, as <hi>Bernard</hi> writeth on the 91. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> are ill lodged and haue a poore Tabernacle, the diuell hath ſoone blowen that away.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt ſort, are the ſuperſtitious Papiſts, who in the time of plague runne to the houſe of the Spider to be preſerued, to ſtickes and ſtones, mettals and papers, Angels and Saints, and principally to Saint <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> for as euery ſickneſſe &amp; diſeaſe hath his Apothecarie and Phyſician among them: So the plague hath Saint <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> vnto whom with their families they runne to bee preſerued. That execrable <hi>Pſalter</hi> of the <hi>Virgine Marie,</hi> compiled by them, maketh her to be this ſecret place whereunto wee ought to runne: the prayer of <hi>Dauid</hi> which he made being viſited with the plague, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly abuſed in this maner, <hi>O Lady rebuke me not in thine anger, neither chaſtiſe me in thy wrath:</hi> The 91. <hi>Pſalme</hi> is in the like maner abuſed. <hi>Who ſo dwelleth in the ſecret of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, &amp;c.</hi> But O ye blind ſeducers of ſoules, it may be firſt a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:180761:12"/>
vnto you all, that neither <hi>Dauid, Iob</hi> or <hi>Ezechiah</hi> viſited with the plague went to Cherub or Seraphin, <hi>Gabriel</hi> or <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phael, Abraham</hi> or <hi>Moſes: whom haue I in heauen but thee?</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid:</hi> he ſaith not, that he had a <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>a Samuel:</hi> haue all theſe erred? Euen ſo will we with them. Secondly, yee goe to them that cannot helpe you, let them ariſe, if they can helpe you in the time of your miſerie, <hi>Iere.</hi> 2. In the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of Samaria, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 6. a woman crying to the King, <hi>helpe me, O King,</hi> hee anſwered, <hi>ſeeing the Lord doth not ſuccour thee, how ſhould I helpe thee?</hi> Concluding ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that if the Lord withdraw his helping hand, it lieth not in the power of mortall man to helpe. So wee may anſwere the Papiſts crying in the time of plague to their <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> helpe and aid vs Saint <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi> If it lieth not in the power of mortall men that are liuing with vs to helpe, how much leſſe can they that are dead? And farre leſſe, one that perhaps <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> hath neuer beene? As for the Angels, they are diſpleaſed that ye come to them, to thruſt vpon them ſuch a dangerous honour: they may ſay as <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 115. <hi>Not vnto vs O Lord, not vnto vs, &amp;c.</hi> they that refuſed a farre ſmaller offer vpon the earth,<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.9.</note> the onely bowing of the knee vnto them <hi>(See thou doe it not)</hi> will bee much more diſcontented, to ſee the knees of the heart to ſtoup to them for the ceaſing of the plague: for although an Angel ſmote ſeuentie thouſand in the time of <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet he was but the inſtrument, God onely the agent, and therefore he onely to be prayed vnto. If the Papiſts reply that they intreate onely Saint <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> to ſpeake vnto God for them;<note place="margin">Obiection. Anſwer.</note> the anſwer is, that God needeth not a <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> nor any Saint ſo euer, to be his Maſter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: this is a ſeruice not vnmeet for the gouernours of the earth? the Lord is not like vnto earthly Princes, vnto the which may be ſaid, that which <hi>Iethro</hi> ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the thing is too heauie for thee, thou art not able to doe it thy ſelfe alone:</hi> for the Almightie is able to doe it alone, neither is there any defect in his hearing, whoſe eares are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the prayers of the poore. Let vs therefore hold Chriſt Ieſus alone for the Maſter of Requeſts; it is he onely that can
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180761:12"/>
preſent our requeſts which we make vnto the Lord for the ceaſing of the plague: let others run where they will, to ſtickes and ſtones from the name of the Lord: I doe you no iniurie to impute this to you, for as <hi>Hilarie</hi> writeth vpon the firſt <hi>Pſalme, It is as great an offence to make a new, as to denie the true God.</hi> The Lord annoynt your eyes with his eye-ſalue, that ye may returne to flie to the name of <hi>Iehouah.</hi> As for vs, we will follow the holy Canon and leaue the broad way, whoſe end is deſtruction, ſaying with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 11.1. <hi>In the Lord put I my truſt, how ſay ye then to my ſoule, flie to your mountain as a bird.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> I end the firſt branch of this diſcourſe with that holy Epipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neme of King <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 146.5. <hi>Bleſſed is hee that hath the God of Iacob for his helpe, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the name of the place, and other circumſtances,<note place="margin">The ſecond part, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the place.</note> there followeth in the two places, the condition, properties, quality and ſafeneſſe of the place whereunto we muſt run in the time of the plague. The ſonnes of men in the time of infection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their departure, haue a ſpeciall regard of the place where they will goe, of the ſituation, nature, and ſuch like, and being led by the preſcription of the Phyſician: Secondly, by their owne minde, they make choyſe commonly of a place in which they perceiue theſe ſeuen properties follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and although <hi>Salomon</hi> here maketh mention but of one, namly of a ſafe place, yet giue me leaue to diſcourſe of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they go where there is a good, wholſome &amp; pure ayre,<note place="margin">1 A pure place.</note> not ſubiect to ſtinking euaporations, &amp; it is the preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Phyſicians, that we ſhould go vnto places where the ayre is not corrupted, far from the infection. <hi>Dauid</hi> fled to ſuch a place, for ſuch is the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> a pure place, far from the corruptions of this world, for he is a pure, &amp; incorruptible God, in whom there is no infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin: the Lord, holy, holy, holy, not admitting thoſe in whoſe mortall bodies the plague of ſin doth raign: to pray then &amp; to repent, is to returne &amp; go to a wholeſom light. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 17.24. The places whereunto the ſons of men flye, although they are for a time corrupted, yet they are not warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſtil ſo to remain, diuers alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry meanes may befall, as by the reſort of perſons infected, &amp; ſuch like: but the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> this place of refuge, ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be altered, for he is the immutable &amp; vncha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable God, <hi>&amp;


<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180761:13"/>
the gates of that Citie no vncleane perſon ſhal enter, Apoc,</hi> 22.14.15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, men make choyſe of a pleaſant and delectable place,<note place="margin">2 A pleaſant place.</note> both for their bodies and ſoules, where there is good companie to recreate themſelues in their ſorrow and exile, foode and neceſſaries for their bodies, further by the riuer ſide, or where there is good water: laſtly, where they may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue food for their ſoules, the word of God Preached. This place of refuge, the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> is a pleaſant and delectable place, where canſt thou better recreate thy ſelfe, then by thy Father and brother Ieſus Chriſt in this thy exile and miſerie? Comfortable is the boſome of the mother to the yong infant, but more comfortable is the name of the Lord to the righteous which are called little babes by the Apoſtle. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh mention in his voyage toward Rome, of a certaine place which was called <hi>(The faire hauens) Act.</hi> 27. this place of refuge better deſerued this name, let vs goe thither, for it is a harbour and rode for thoſe which are toſſed in the ſea and deluge of the Peſtilence: happy is the ſoule that landeth at theſe hauens. If we deſire water, there is the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life: Iere.</hi> 2. <hi>the water of grace, Pſal.</hi> 51. If we deſire the word; there is <hi>the word it ſelfe, Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Ioh. 1 <hi>the truth Ioh.</hi> 14. There is the beſt, the firſt, the ancienteſt Preacher, God himſelfe that preached in Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in our choyſe we ſeeke out a ſafe place, whither we may goe without danger,<note place="margin">3 A ſafe place.</note> and where we may abide ſafe, and dwell without danger. The name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> is a ſafe harbour, the ſecret place and ſhadow of the moſt high, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1. vnder whoſe wings we ſhall abide ſafe and harmeleſſe. Three things prooue the ſafeneſſe of this place: Firſt, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> name of the place, it is <hi>A ſtrong towre, Prou.</hi> 18.10. <hi>A ſecret place, Pſal.</hi> 32.7. <hi>A rocke and fortreſſe, Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible.</hi> Such are not the fortreſſes of mortall men, which they are conſtrained to render vp, being driuen thereunto ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by famine, or force, as <hi>Seba</hi> in the time of <hi>Dauid</hi> hereof is a witneſſe. Secondly, the Lord of the ſoyle, which inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that place, his name is <hi>Iehouah:</hi> the Almightie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1. the ſtrong and inuincible God, who will and is able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs. Thirdly, it is prooued by the ſucceſſe of thoſe who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180761:13"/>
run to it, &amp; by that which they receiue, they are exalted, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued or deliuered (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) which <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.7. and is confirmed by the ſucceſſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> prayer, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.25. <hi>and the plague ceaſed from Iſrael.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable is the ſaying of <hi>Dauid; Pſal.</hi> 91.3.15.16. in which, ſixe things prooue the happie ſucceſſe of the righteous that runneth vnto it. Firſt, Gods ready anſwere: Secondly, his preſence: Thirdly, his deliuerance: Fourthly, his aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to honour: Fiftly, length of dayes: Sixtly, fruition of ſaluation: O the excellent riches, pleaſures, and ioyes which the righteous there ſhall enioy. As <hi>Lot</hi> there fled vnto little Zoar to be preſerued from the fire of <hi>Sodome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> So let vs flie to the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> to be ſafe from the fire of the plague. The earthly places whereunto men run, do want this proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: they are not warranted to be ſafe there, either from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or from the plague, and the experience of this yeere doth declare it vnto vs all. Some haue returned and ſome haue died there, but as for the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> thy ſoule is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to be preſerued, if thither ſhee taketh her recourſe; and as they onely eſcaped the flood, that entred into the Arke of <hi>Noah:</hi> So likewiſe, they that enter into this incorruptible and immortall Arke, ſhall only be ſafegarded from the deluge of afflictions. The Doue of <hi>Noah</hi> at her firſt flight from the Arke, although ſhee mounted aloft, and fetched many retires, yet ſhee could finde no reſting, vntill ſhee returned againe to the Arke: So the poore ſoule may flie where ſhee will, but yet ſhee ſhall not haue any ſure footing to reſt, except ſhee returne to the heauenly Arke: let vs therefore be wiſe as Serpents, and ſimple as Doues, for as they being perſecuted, flie vnto the rockes; ſo let vs in our calamities take our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the rocke of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 18.2. neuer haue there bin holes in the rockes ſo open for the doue, as the name of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah</hi> for the righteous ſoules. There are two renowmed places mentioned by <hi>Plinie, Locris, and Crotone,</hi> where the plague was neuer, as he writeth <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 96. and without doubt many reſorted thither: but although we ſhould flie at this day to <hi>Locris</hi> and <hi>Crotone,</hi> if wee carrie within vs the plague of ſinne, the inward cauſe of the bodily contagion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180761:14"/>
we haue no warrant to bee ſafegarded. But me thinkes I heare a controuerſie:<note place="margin">Obiection.</note> Many righteous haue fled to the name of the Lord, and yet haue not beene ſafe from the deluge of the peſtilence, or from the ſnare of the hunter: but thouſands, and thouſands are fallen in former viſitations, yea ſome of the choſen of Iſrael.<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> The anſwer is, that they haue firſt obtained, either that which they prayed for; ſecondly, or that which is better; or thirdly, that which is ſufficient And the Lord hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs alwayes, although alwayes he granteth not our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this ſeemeth a Paradox and yet the trueth thereof is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: for in ſteed of that we asked, he giueth vs a better thing, and a better place: <hi>thou askeſt the earth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>the Lord giueth thee heauen: temporall life, &amp; he giueth thee the eternal.</hi> The Surgion that ſaweth off the arme or legge of the Patient, who crieth for impatience &amp; apprehenſion; heareth him, <hi>Non ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voluntatem, ſed ſanitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> not according to his wil but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his health:<note place="margin">4. A place where they haue friends.</note> &amp; ſo the Lord dealeth with his Patients.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to proceed, men make choice of places where they haue their friends: the children reſort to their parents, the parents to their children, brethren to their brethren, and one friend to another. The name of the Lord is a place of refuge where we haue our beſt friends, there we haue our Father, our eldeſt brother Chriſt Ieſus, the holy Ghoſt our comforter: and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> in the time of Plague went to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable place.<note place="margin">Experience hereof Anno 1625.</note> In earthly places vnto which the ſonnes of men reſort, either we haue no friends, or they are farre off, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſeeke other: or ſometimes although we haue friends, yet they will not receiue vs for feere of infection: but in this holy temple, and vpon this holy mountaine, we are ſure to finde at all times the aforeſaid friends.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. A place acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for all men.</note>Fiftly, we haue regard to chooſe a place which is lawful for all men to come vnto, which is not prohibited or forbidden by the Lord of the ſoyle and Magiſtrate of the place, and where we know we ſhall be receiued. This place of refuge is ſuch, acceſſible for all men, for <hi>whoſoeuer ſhall call on the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued, Ioel.</hi> 2.32. Neuer a citie of refuge ſo free for all manner of tranſgreſſions: hither may come the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180761:14"/>
King and the ſubiect, the rich and the poore, the learned and the vnlearned, the merchant and the tradeſman: the ſound and the ſicke, yea the infected with the plague. In the time of infection, it is not lawfull for them that dwell where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion reigneth, to com vnto the Princes Court, they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Proclamation to reſort thither. But the court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is open for all men, yea the for infected, for they cannot infect the Court of heauen:<note place="margin">The King of heauen his proclamation.</note> the King of heauen hath made a Proclamation in the 50. <hi>Pſal.</hi> that we ſhould reſort thither, &amp; the Prince of glory Ieſus Chriſt who keepeth his reſidence there, will not keepe vs backe. If the Prince had made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation that the infected ſhould reſort to his court to bee healed, who would not haſten thither? It was not lawfull for all men to come to the inner Court of King <hi>Ahaſſuerus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 4.</note> none might approach but they to whom hee held out his golden Scepter, except he would die the death that was appointed for ſuch as durſt come neere: no ſuch kind of puniſhment is appointed for thoſe that goe vnto the Courte of the King of heauen, we may <hi>approach boldely to the throne of grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our King (I meane not that <hi>yron ſcepter</hi> of his iuſtice,) but the <hi>golden</hi> of his mercie, is euer held forth to man, woman, children, bond or free, ſtranger or Citizen, infected or not infected, whether they be called, or not called: and they all may ſafely approach: I name not neither inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward court, but euen <hi>to the throne of grace,</hi> where the King himſelfe ſitteth: and if there we craue of him, I ſay not to the halfe of his Kingdome (as <hi>Ahaſſuerus</hi> ſpake vnto Eſter) but to the whole, it ſhall not bee denied vs. Feare of puniſhment keepeth vs from the Princes court. Let not feare keepe vs from the court of heauen.<note place="margin">Nehem 2.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> although hee held the cup to the King, yet how fearefull hee was to make a requeſt vnto him: But as for you O ye righteous ſoules, <hi>feare yee not, O you little flocke, for it is your fathers pleaſrue to giue you a Kingdome. Luk.</hi> 12. Further in time of contagion, not only the court but alſo the other cities, townes and villages, will not often lodge them that come from contagious places, either the Lord of the ſoile, or the magiſtrate of thoſe places forbidding it; but as for that heauenly Ieruſalem, and the Lord of the liuing, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180761:15"/>
euery one may reſort, the Lord and magiſtrate of heauen doth not interdict it. <hi>Dauid</hi> cried vnto the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>thou art my portion in the land of the liuing. Pſal.</hi> 142.5. At Rome the houſen of the <hi>Aediles,</hi> were alwaies open for all men, that they might reſort thither, to haue their cauſes heard: and ſo is the houſe of the Lord for the afflicted ſoules. In ſome places there are appointed (as I my ſelfe haue ſeene) watchmen with halbards, to aske the paſſengers from whence they come, and ſometimes to keepe out thoſe that come from infected places, but in our going to this place, we need not to haue ſuch feare, for as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hic non eſt miles aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtens qui expellat, here there is no Sergiant or Soldier to keepe thee out.</hi> If the cities of the earth ſhut their gates before thee, thou canſt not enter. As for that heauenly Ieruſalem, it is not lockt, and although it were, prayer, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, is a key to open heauen, &amp; to bring thee to the preſence of God. <hi>Serm.</hi> 226. <hi>detemp.</hi> the Towne and Villages in times of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection although they receiue ſome, yet they will not harbour many: and often there is no place for multitudes: but ſo is it not with the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> with this ſtrong tower, it is not like vnto the bulwarkes of mortall men, into the which if too many enter, they will hinder one another; this fortreſſe can receiue millions and millions without any impediment. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the temple is alſo interdicted to the infected, for they are commanded by the magiſtrate to keepe their houſen for a time, or if they come, they are entreated to ſit a ſide: but the Lords holy temple aboue in heauen, is not forbidden vnto the infected, nor to any man: it is lawfull for them to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and pray, and that with the ſucceſſe of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>In my trouble I did call vpon the Lord and cried vnto my God, and he heard my voyce out of his Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. A place neere vnto the Citie</note>Sixtly, ſome make a choyſe in the plague time, of a place which is neere, whereunto they may eaſily goe without any great trouble or coſt: the name of the Lord is ſuch a place, compendious to cut off vnneceſſarie labours, yee need not to runne farre, <hi>the Lord is neere,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaketh; <hi>to all them that call vpon him:</hi> neither will it coſt vs any thing, mony or merites, interceſſion of friends or gifts: Poore men,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180761:15"/>
yee that want friendes or money, and therefore cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide your ſelues a place, be not diſmaide, behold, here is a place which will coſt you nothing. It is a place whereunto we may go at all times, at dinner time, and at ſupper, as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh, in the day time, and at mid-night, in thy health, and in thy ſickneſſe: the ſicke man may ly downe vpon his bed and goe vnto it, and when with King <hi>Ezekiah</hi> he cannot vſe the feet of the fleſh, yet may he vſe the feet of the ſpirit. In a moment we can flie thither, for as ſoone as we haue finiſhed our prayer, we are alreadie come to this place, and to the Lord of this ſoyle, our prayer and God meeting one another in heauen, as Ieſus Chriſt and the woman at the Well, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. As for earthly places whereunto men reſort, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are far off, vneaſie to goe vnto, and that with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and coſt, or expences, ſometimes we are ſtopped, we muſt haue Warrants and Certificates of the Pariſh &amp; Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, that our houſe is not infected, before we can be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: all this trouble we need not in the time of plague in our going to the name of the Lord: nothing will ſtop vs, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily plague ſhall be no impediment, for wee haue a warrant that we may paſſe, the King of heauen his warrant in the 50: <hi>Pſalme, Call vpon me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The warrant of the infected.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore this place is better then the earthly, where the fearefull ſonnes of men dwell which feare the apparrel, houſhold-ſtuffe, yea and thy letters: I know nothing then to ſtop our paſſage, but the plague of the ſoule, as the Lord of this ſoyle telleth vs in the, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Touch none vncleane thing, and I will receiue you.</hi> But I heare the weake conſcience obiect,<note place="margin">Obiection.</note> I am infected with the plague of the ſoule, and therefore it is not lawfull for me to call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord: it is for the righteous as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh: but alas, I am vnrighteous, and how can I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go vnto this ſtrong tower? The anſwer is,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort O weake conſcience, that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh not of them that are righteous by their owne righteouſneſſe, but by the righteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus: ſuch are all the faithful in whoſe mortall bodies the plague of ſin doth not remaine, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities being healed by <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician, <hi>Pſal</hi> 103. If yee deſire a certificate thereof, you haue the Goſpell, ſubſcribed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180761:16"/>
and ſealed by God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt. If yee deſire a witneſſe, ye haue a threefold witneſſe, <hi>The ſpirit, the water and the bloud,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. A place where we may haue a Phyſician.</note>Laſtly, wee make choyſe of ſuch places, where if need be, we may haue good Phyſicians, for we eſteeme it a great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to be deſtitute of a good Phyſician, and of meanes to helpe vs in our neede. The place of refuge whereunto <hi>Dauid</hi> fled, and wee alſo ought to flie, following his direction, hath the beſt Phyſician which is both in heauen or earth, God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician, who hath both health and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, life and death in his power, to diſpoſe of them for our good and ſaluation: knocke therefore boldly with the hand of prayer and repentance at the gate of his mercie, and thruſt in his hands, both thy life and health. And thus much for the qualities and properties of the place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To pray for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is alſo requiſite.</note>Further, we haue to obſerue that <hi>Dauid</hi> went not to this place of refuge alone, but with his whole family, for he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Elders of the people, for the people, and for the deliuerance of his whole kingdome. Herein imitate King <hi>Dauid,</hi> remember in thy prayer thy whole family, and the ſtate of the whole kingdome, the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Leui.</hi> There are foure ſorts for which we muſt pray: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1:"/> Firſt, for thoſe which are <hi>Supra nos,</hi> aboue vs: Secondly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for thoſe which are equall vnto vs. Thirdly, for thoſe which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are <hi>Sub nobis,</hi> vnder vs: Fourthly, for thoſe which are <hi>Contra <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> nos,</hi> againſt vs. In the going to the name of the Lord, wee muſt not imitate the negligence of many, who depart into the Country, and care onely for themſelues; as for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, or at leaſt their ſeruants, they are not once mindfull of them: but we muſt as well carrie with vs in our prayers, the ſeruants which are vnder vs, as ſhee that lieth in our boſome: <hi>And the Oliue plants which are round about our tables, Pſal.</hi> 108.3. The Athenians would offer ſacrifice, but onely for their owne Citie, and their neighbours of <hi>Chios:</hi> but wee Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt pray, not onely for the mother Citie, but for all the daughters: Chriſt teacheth vs to ſay, <hi>Our father, &amp;c.</hi> as if wee all came from one wombe. It is a principle both of nature and policie, <hi>Vis vnita fortior,</hi> Strength vnited, receiueth more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180761:16"/>
ſtrength. It holdeth likewiſe in Diuinitie. If the prayer of one righteous perſon auaileth much, the prayer of many righteous ſhall auaile more. If the <hi>Syrophenician</hi> obtained for her daughter the ſute ſhee made, much more the whole Church of England ſhal obtaine for all her daughters: <hi>Where two or three be gathered together in his name, he is in the midſt of them.</hi> Much rather in the midſt of a people, in the midſt of thouſands, in whom there is <hi>Anima vna, cor vnum:</hi> One ſoule, one heart, one tongue, as if they were all but one man. Lord, heale the ſores of our land, for behold, both the mother and the daughters, the head and the members doe proſtrate our ſelues before his Maieſtie. Yee of the ſect of <hi>Rome,</hi> diuide not at this time of the plague in your prayers, the ſoule, the voyce and language of the Countrey into two places. <hi>Eliah</hi> and his companie, praying in one place and with one ſtile: <hi>O Lord God of Abraham,</hi> and yee in another: <hi>O</hi> Baal <hi>heale vs:</hi> Some praying for the life of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and ſome for the life of <hi>Iabin.</hi> As for vs, we will pray for the Lords annoynted our Soueraigne, that God may hide Him vnder the ſhadow of his wings from the noyſome peſtilence, knowing that this is one of the parts of our obedience towards him, that we (as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great taught his ſouldiers to ſhew their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance in nothing more then this) ſhould pray for him, yea, for his royal Conſort, his hopeful poſterity &amp; their Families. I end this point, with the ſaying of an ancient Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: That there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s no better Guard, or Halbards to ſafegard a Prince, than the prayers of the Righteous.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the third branch of this diſcourſe,<note place="margin">Three rules to be obſerued in our going to this place.</note> giue leaue Chriſtian Readers to the ſpirituall Phyſicians, to lay downe three rules, which are to be obſerued in this our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall departure to the name of the Lord. The bodily Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians touching departure preſcribe (as is before ſaid) three rules <hi>Longè citò, tarde:</hi> Goe farre off, depart ſpeedily returne ſlowly. The ſame rules are to be obſerued by the righteous:<note place="margin">1: <hi>Longè.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, we muſt flie far, not with the prodigall &amp; forlorne ſon in a far Countrey, far from the feare of God and thought of death, or with <hi>Ionah</hi> from the preſence of the Lord, who ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180761:17"/>
on the Cherubins &amp; can ouertake vs: for whither ſhall I goe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 839.9.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> from thy ſpirit? Or whither ſhall I flee from thy preſence? But farre from this world and the earth, vnto the holy temple and mountaine, vnto heauen which is high aboue the earth, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103, 11. vnto that place which is called the <hi>land of the liuing.</hi> Secondly, flie farre from the plague of ſinne, and the infected ayre of this world, and being come vnto that farre Countrey, the Lord of the ſoyle will receiue you.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Citò.</hi>
               </note> The ſecond rule is, flie ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and deferre not your departure: which rule is not in any maner to be omitted, it is the counſell of the wiſe man <hi>Ieſus Syrach, Eccle.</hi> 38.9. <hi>My ſonne faile not in thy ſickneſſe but pray vnto the Lord, and he will make thee whole.</hi> Tis the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord <hi>to call vpon him in the time of need, Pſal.</hi> 50. Which muſt be performed with ſpeed, according to the example of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>I will runne the way of thy Commandements.</hi> If wee make haſt to flie into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and forget to goe ſpeedily vnto this Sanctuarie. it is as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of another matter, <hi>Curſus celerrimus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter viam:</hi> A ſwift race beſides the way. Haſt in this matter is praiſe worthy, &amp; a man can neuer run too faſt that runneth to this place. The delay that <hi>Elizeus</hi> made, let me go kiſſe my Father, &amp; thoſe ſhifts in the Goſpel: Let me firſt go burie my mother, or take leaue of my friends, are not admitted in this buſineſſe: commune not therfore with fleſh &amp; blood. If in the time of plague, we make ſuch haſte to depart, before we haue ordained our buſineſſe aright, or bad our friends farwel: How much more ought we to haſten our ſpiritual voyage? While the fal-bridge is let downe, let vs make ſpeed to enter. Many, becauſe they went not far, nor made ſpeed to depart, haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered their bodies, but many more, becauſe they fled not from the contagion of ſin with ſpeed, haue endangered their ſoules: &amp; therfore as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. of another matter, ſo I may ſay of this going: <hi>So run that yee may obtaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Tardè.</hi>
               </note>The third rule is, Returne ſlowly: that is, continue where thou art: a neceſſarie rule to be obſerued in the going to the name of the Lord. It is the rule of the ſpirituall Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180761:17"/>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Pray continually, &amp;c.</hi> As it is preſcribed, ſo it hath beene practiſed:<note place="margin">Luk. 21.36.</note> the woman of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan continued in her prayer, and returned not in haſt. They which are in the Countrey, although there bee many things which might mooue them to returne, yet for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their bodies, they continue till the plague be ceaſed: So continue in thy prayer by the Lord, and be not wearie of wel doing. Although three things might haue mooued the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rophenician</hi> to returne, the ſilence of Chriſt, her back-friends, and the odious names giuen vnto her, yet theſe diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments her poore ſoule digeſted, obtaining both a cure for her daughters infirmitie, and a commendation for her faith. O woman thou haſt wrought a miracle by the preſeuerance of thy prayer, and haſt giuen to thy Sauiour occaſion to doe a memorable act, conuenient to his nature, glorious to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name. Let vs at this time follow her perſeuerance, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lord ſhould ſeeme to be ſilent for a time, yet let vs not draw backe, that we may receiue a cure both for our ſoules and bodies, and deſerue a commendation both by God and other nations, and thereby giue occaſion vnto the Lord to ſhew his omnipotent power in the ceaſing of the plague: and to doe an act in England conuenient to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and glorious to his holy name. And as <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtled with the Angel and would not let him goe vntill he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the bleſſing: So let vs as it were ſtriue with the Lord by our prayers, and let him not goe vntill he haue heard vs, in that which we aske of him in this afflicted time. Let our prayers be now as the ſhowers of the raine, if the firſt ſhowre faileth of watering the earth ſufficiently: the ſecond, the third or the fourth, wil fulfill the thirſt thereof. Let vs be like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the widow, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. and our importunitie will draw him vnto audience: but yet let vs hold a better opinion of the Iudge of the world, then of a common vulgar friend, It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted his eares to heare our redoubled obſecrations, and he ſuſpendeth our deſires in expectation, that we ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate to craue. The bodily Phyſician cannot away with the importunate patient: but God,<note place="margin">Habak. 2.3</note> King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180761:18"/>
loueth the importunate prayer, &amp; more acceptable is to him the end of our prayer then the beginning. I would the children of light were as wiſe in their generation, as the wodden Prieſts, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. who cried long to <hi>Baal:</hi> yea cut themſelues with kniues that they might be heard: and what ought not wee then doe to obtaine our ſuite? Let nothing then mooue vs to returne: but as the King of the Philiſtines, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. though they had Calues at home, yet they kept the ſtraight way to <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> and held one path: turning neither to the right, nor to the left hand; neither euer ſtood ſtill, till they came into the field of <hi>Ioſuah.</hi> So in our going to the name of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> the affection of our ſoules bearing the Arke and coffer of our ſuite, though it hath worldly allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to draw it backe, as the Kine had Calues: yet let it in the way to the houſe of God, as they to <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> hold one path of perſeuerance, turning neither to the right or left hand with wandring cogitations, till it commeth into the field and garden of God, and there let it remaine. Many heretofore hauing not continued in the Countrey, in their haſty retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning haue fallen ſicke, and died: So many hauing not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in this ſtrong bulwarke, haue endangered both body and ſoule. And thus much hitherto of the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third part containing the houſhold ſtuffe which we muſt carrie vnto that place.</note>There followeth now the third and the laſt, which ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto vs the houſhold-ſtuffe which we muſt carrie with vs thither noted in the word <hi>(Righteous.)</hi> As they which goe in the country in the time of plague carrie with them their houſhold-ſtuffe, their furniture, and thoſe things which are neceſſarie for their bodies, and as <hi>Noah</hi> entring the Arke, carried with him neceſſaries; ſo likewiſe in our going to this place, we muſt carrie with vs thoſe things which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for our ſoules, that wee may be receiued by the Lord of that ſoyle, and without which we cannot goe thither. There are fiue peeces of ſpirituall houſhold-ſtuffe which are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for vs,<note place="margin">1. Repentance.</note> noted in the word <hi>Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>Repentance</hi> and holines of life, for hee that is righteous giueth himſelf to righteouſnes. And this furniture carried with him <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.11. As they which goe in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180761:18"/>
the country haue their reaſons why they carrie with them ſuch and ſuch neceſſaries: So giue me leaue in the opening of this furniture, to ſhew you alſo the reaſons which muſt moue vs to carie them with vs. As for this firſt,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> the firſt reaſon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is, the preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpiritual Phyſicians, it is the Apoſtles precept: Let euery one that calleth on the name of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquitie. The ſecond is, that we may be receiued,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for the righteous Lord l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueth righteouſneſſe: his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance doth behold the iuſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.7. His eyes are vpon the righteous, and his eares open to their cry, but his face is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that doe euill,<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18.</note> to cut off their remembrance from the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.15.16. <hi>If I regarde wickedneſſe in my heart</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, the Lord will not heare me.</hi> For as <hi>Salomon</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>the Lord is farre off from the wicked, but he heareth the prayer of the righteous. Prou.</hi> 15.29. Draw therefore neere to God, and he will draw neere to you: cleanſe your handes ye ſinners, and purge your hearts ye wauering minded.<note place="margin">Prou. 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.8.9. The third is, that the bodily plague may ceaſe, for how <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> dare we approach vnto the Lord, to craue that it might be remooued, and yet carie with vs the inward cauſe thereof: let the Phyſicians <hi>maxime</hi> heere preuaile, remooue the cauſe, that the effect may ceaſe. Let vs not as the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> bring into the preſence of our father,<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.</note> the garment of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> which we our ſelues haue be blooded. As <hi>Aaron</hi> could not come before the Lord before he was waſhed, ſo let vs not go vnto him before we haue cleanſed our ſelues from infection of the ſoule. And as <hi>Iacob Gen.</hi> 42. exhorted his ſonnes, when they were going to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> carry with you the beſt fruits of the land and giue them him: ſo let vs in our going to the true <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, carrie with vs the beſt fruites of our hearts to offer vp the ſacrifice of our prayers, leauing our corrupt affections, as <hi>Abraham</hi> left behinde him at the foot of the hil his aſſes. I conclude this firſt point with the ſaying of <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, as in a garland, it is not enough that the flowers be pure and cleane, but the hand alſo which handleth them:</hi> ſo it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient that the words of our prayers be holy, but the heart alſo which conceiueth them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:180761:19"/>
               <note place="margin">2. Faith.</note>The ſecond piece of houſhold-ſtuffe <hi>(Faith)</hi> for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is alſo hee that beleeueth in Chriſt, and is righteous through the righteouſnes of Chriſt the righteous.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.</note> This fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture carried <hi>Dauid</hi> with him, for as hee had a deſire of health and remiſſion of his ſinne, ſo hee had alſo a ſtedfaſt faith and confidence that it ſhould be forgiuen him. This perſuaſion of deliuerance, and hope of obtaining, we muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> haue with vs enterteining it in our hearts. The reaſons are, firſt the preſcription of the ſpirituall Phyſicians, it is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles precept, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Let him aske in faith and wauer not.</hi> And in the fourth to the <hi>Heb.</hi> 16. that we ſhould <hi>goe boldely to the throne of grace: drawing neere vnto him with a true heart in aſſurance of faith,</hi> Heb. 10.22. <hi>caſting not away that confidence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which hath recompence of reward, Verſ.</hi> 35. tis the counſaile of Chriſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.24. Secondly, carrie it with thee, that thou maiſt receiue that, <hi>for which thou goeſt vnto him faithfully. Pſal.</hi> 145.18. And <hi>whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske in prayer, if yee beleeue yee ſhall receiue it. Math.</hi> 21.22. Without this, there is no going thither. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. But as righteouſnes and trueth kiſſe each other, ſo muſt prayer and faith, which is the ground of prayer: firſt beleeue, and then ſpeake, this was the order of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 116. this faith will make vs acceptable to the Lord of that ſoile, and make vs finde fauour at his hands: Faith is a beautifull queene, as highly fauored of the King of Kings, as euer <hi>Eſther</hi> was of King <hi>Ahaſſuerus:</hi> ſhe ſhall not be ſtayed without at the gate, but with an humble preſumption, may approach into the inner court, and ſhall receiue her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: for if we ſhall <hi>receiue a kingdome, Luk.</hi> 12. how much more that which is leſſe, being asked by faith? come not then without this aduocate. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>de Idol. vanit.</hi> ſayeth, (ſpeaking how he and his brethren did much good in the viſitation of the ſicke) <hi>prout fides patientis adiuuat, aut gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia curantis aſpirat,</hi> that he proſpered according as they and the patient had faith to ſpeake vnto God: the greateſt enemie to the efficacie of our prayer is diſtruſtfulnes. And therefore <hi>God forbid</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine that what wee deſire God to doe for vs with our mouthes, we ſhould deny him to be able to doe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180761:19"/>
in our hearts.</hi> A heathen man <hi>Seneca</hi> could ſay,<note place="margin">in Hippolito.</note> he that asketh fearefully and doubtfull, teacheth him to denie of whom he asketh: and men doubting they ſhall not obtaine, make God vnwilling to heare them. As vnbeleefe did ſhut the doore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iewes that ſome of them enter not into <hi>Canaan,</hi> a tipe of heauenly Ieruſalem; ſo diſtruſtfulnes is able to ſhut our praier out of that heauenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> And therefore as <hi>Iacob</hi> going to his father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to receiue the bleſſing, put on the garment of his eldeſt brother, ſo let vs going to our heauenly father to obtaine our requeſt, be cloathed with faith through the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of our eldeſt brother Ieſus Chriſt. Further, this confidence giueth vs entrie into that place. Open the gates, ſaith the prophet, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 26.2. that the righteous Nation which keepeth faith, may enter in. Faith is a key that openeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the gates of the citie. Thirdly, this furniture is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for the feet which muſt beare vs thither, that they may be firme, ſtedfaſt, and faile vs not in the way: the moiſture and iuice whereby the ſpiritual feet of our prayers are nouriſhed, is faith. By faith yee ſtand, ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. It is the root that beareth vs, the legges and ſupporters, and the ſtrong men that hold vs vp that we fall not. As the Doues neſt is in the clefts of rockes that cannot be aſſaulted, ſo faith reſteth it ſelf in the wounds of Chriſt, it caſteth an anchor in knowledge of the true God, and ſtandeth as firme, as mount Sion that cannot be remooued. Fourthly, we muſt carrie it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> with vs, that we may liue: why doe we with our houſhold-ſtuffe goe into the Countrey, but becauſe we are deſirous of life? If in the going to the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> for remiſſion of ſinne and ſpirituall life, and for the remoouing of the effect of ſinne, the bodily contagion, we are deſirous of it, we muſt not forget this furniture, for by Faith we liue, <hi>Abac.</hi> 2. <hi>It is the life of the ſoule, and the ſoule and ſpirit of the new man.</hi> Wee may haue a name that wee liue, but indeede wee are dead to God-ward, if wee beleeue not: doubting then neither of might, mercie, or of his promiſe, becauſe they are paſſed by couenant, oath, before vnmooueable witneſſes, the beſt in heauen, and the beſt in earth, and becauſe they are ſigned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180761:20"/>
with the finger of the holy Ghoſt, and ſealed with the blood of his annoynted and beloued let vs with a holy confidence runne to this place in this afflicted time of the contagion, that we may receiue mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Humilitie.</note>The third peece neceſſarie for our voyage is <hi>(Humilitie)</hi> which excludeth all opinion of our owne worthineſſe and righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> carried his furniture with him, yea this royall ornament: as appeareth out of two things. Firſt, out of the tearme and phraſe of obſeruation <hi>(I beſeech you)</hi> a proper terme of ſubmiſſion, and the poore ſuters phraſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, out of his bodily proſtrating of himſelfe in ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath with the Elders of Iſrael. 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21. Herein let vs in this time of plague imitate King <hi>Dauid</hi> in our going to the name of the Lord, carrying with vs this ornament, this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and lowlyneſſe: let vs vſe the poore ſuters phraſe &amp; not pride of ſpeech: ſaying we are worthie O Lord: let vs not goe thither to bragge as many runne into Country to the dominiere; but let vs pray that the Lord will giue vs with vs this ſubmiſſion, that we may bow not only the knees of our bodies, but of our hearts: yea, that we may euen bow the very phraſe of our words with <hi>Dauid,</hi> that wee may vtter them as if the ſmalleſt Graſhopper of the earth were to ſpeak with feare and reuerence before that dreadfull Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Three things muſt mooue vs to carry it with vs in this our voyage: Firſt, the perſon to whom we goe, his greatneſſe, excellencie, Maieſtie, his glorious name which is <hi>Iehouah.</hi> It was the counſel that <hi>Aeſope</hi> gaue to <hi>Solon,</hi> enquiring what ſpeech he ſhould vſe before <hi>Craeſus:</hi> either very little, or very ſweet, ſaid he. If when we goe to the Princes of the earth, who are but ſmoake and vanitie, wee ſpeake with humilitie, much more doth the preſence of the moſt high God require <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it. Secondly, the conſideration of our owne perſons which doe goe thither: the conſcience of our owne vnworthineſſe and deformitie of ſinne wherewith we are ſpotted: let vs then with <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpeaking to the Lord,<note place="margin">Gen. 18</note> confeſſe that we are but duſt and aſhes. Let vs as <hi>Lazarus</hi> with all our vlcers (which are many in the time of plague) and withall our ſores detec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180761:20"/>
and laide open: lie before the gates of him who is rich in mercy, lamenting, crauing, and beſeeching to be refreſhed. Chriſtians, learne of Chriſt to pray, who although there was no vnworthineſſe in him, yet hee kneeled, fell vpon the ground, the footſtoole of his owne Maieſtie, and lay vpon his face, which neuer Angel beheld without reuerence. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> third is, that our comming to him, may bee acceptable, and that we may receiue the health we ſue for. <hi>To him looketh the Lord, that is poore, and of a contrite ſpirit, Eſa.</hi> 66.2. which hee will not deſpiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>for he is neere vnto them that are of a contrite heart, and will ſaue ſuch as be afflicted in ſpirit, Pſal.</hi> 34.18. The prayer of him that humbleth himſelfe,<note place="margin">Eccle. 35.17.</note> goeth through the clouds: the Lords mercy can onely giue vs the twofold health which we ſue for at this time: now this mercy to whom doth he giue it, but to the humble? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is both grace it ſelfe, and a veſſell to comprehend other graces: and ſhe emptying her ſelfe by a modeſt eſtimation of her owne gifts, is filled againe by the Lord. Let vs now belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as it were ſtriue by humility with the Lord, according to the policy of <hi>Iacob:</hi> Let vs winne by yeelding, and the lower we ſtoupe towards the ground, the more aduantage we ſhall get to obtaine. The Lord to whom we goe, if this humility be in vs, will both dwell with vs and in vs. <hi>O Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtine, how high art thou, and yet the humble of heart, are thine houſes to dwell in:</hi> The proud Phariſie, <hi>Luk</hi> 18. went vnto the Lord without his furniture, praying with pride and with a ſcornefull demonſtration, and therefore returned not iuſtified as the Publican. O that we had not for the moſt part of vs all ſuch Phariſaicall eye browes, whether we talke with God or man, that we might heare that comfortable voice which was ſpoken vnto <hi>Daniel, Feare not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 10 12,</note> 
               <hi>for from the firſt day that thou diddeſt humble thy ſelfe before thy God, thy words were heard.</hi> Let vs therefore vſe to conclude this point: this humble ſtile of <hi>Dauid,</hi> it hath beene the ſtile of a King: and although it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth inglorious, yet it hath beene the ſtile of the glorious Saints of God: it will giue vs the honour of Saints, and raiſe vs from the duſt, ſet vs vpon the thrones, and if it pleaſe the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180761:21"/>
Lord to take vs away by the plague, it will place vs with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: let vs not then brethren forget it, that the anger of the Lord may ceaſe, and that with ioy hereafter wee may ſing with <hi>Marie</hi> in her Canticle, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. <hi>Hee hath regarded the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of his handmaide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Feruencie and zeale.</note>The fourth piece of houſhold-ſtuffe, is <hi>Reuerence, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, zeale</hi> and <hi>feruencie.</hi> For the noyſe of our lips, if it bee as the ringing of Baſons, a vocall modulation, without cordiall meditation, it cannot procure vs audience: for it is as the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the halt and the lame, a body without a ſoule: it is the counſell of the wiſe man, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Bee not raſh with thy mouth, nor let thine heart be haſtie to vtter a thing before God.</hi> Our prayers muſt not bee a formall ſeruice onely, but the ſighes of our ſoules muſt bee ſent with an earneſt meſſage to the eares of God: they muſt not be perfunctorie and cold, rather of cuſtome then of deuotion: for a prayer from fained lips, will returne empty into the boſome that ſent it vp. When wee goe to this place, let vs not goe, as if our ſoules and tongues were ſtrangers, the one not knowing what the other doth: our lips babling without, and our heart not pricked with any inward compunction, for elſe it is as the altar with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fire: a perfunctorie prayer, is as the prayer of the Parret. <hi>Iohannes Fridericus</hi> the Prince of <hi>Saxonia</hi> had a Parret who could rehearſe the Latine <hi>Pater noſter.</hi> Cardinall <hi>Aſcanius</hi> had another, who rehearſed the <hi>Creed,</hi> repreſenting perhaps the faith and praying of his Maſter. What are the careleſſe deuotions of thoſe, who leaue their ſpirits as it were in a ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber while they are a praying, but like vnto thoſe two Parrets babbling; as they muſt bee deuote, ſo muſt they be feruent, kindled by a burning zeale, inflamed with feruent loue: and as the Harts bray after the water brookes, ſo muſt our ſoules after the liuing God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> 
               <hi>For the prayer of a righteous man auaileth much, &amp;c. if it be feruent, Iam</hi> 5.16. If wee are deſirous to know the neceſſity of this zeale and feruencie, receiue theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> directions following. Firſt, the example of Chriſt biddeth vs goe thither with this zeale: Chriſtians receiue directions for the framing of this holy exerciſe from Chriſt, who offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180761:21"/>
vp prayers <hi>with ſtrong crying and teares, Heb.</hi> 5. hee that was the mighty Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> hath roared in his ſupplications. Secondly, the ſpirit of God biddeth vs goe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thither with zeale, for <hi>hee maketh requeſts in our names with grones not to be expreſſed, Rom.</hi> 8. Thirdly, the Maieſtie of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the ſacred Lord of Hoſts, to whom we flye: the royaltie of his nature, ſublimitie of his place, dominion ouer Angels, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs goe thither with zeale. Fourthly, the view of our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> mortalitie and of our ſin, by which we haue cauſed the Lords deſtroying Angell to vnſheath, biddeth vs to goe thither with zeale. Laſtly, the hope and expectation of ſucceſſe, the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie and tenderneſſe of the eares of God, and the precious fauour of his countenance, which muſt bee wiſely intreated and carefully ſought for, biddeth vs to goe thither with zeale, vnleſſe we will ſow, and not reape: plant Vines and not drinke the wine thereof.</p>
            <p>The fift and laſt piece of houſhold-ſtuffe,<note place="margin">5 Patience.</note> is <hi>Chriſtian patience,</hi> a ſubmiſſion vnto his holy will and pleaſure, a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue proper vnto the righteous. <hi>Dauid</hi> carried it with him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and wee muſt not leaue it behinde vs, following the ſtreames of our fooliſh appetites:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> we muſt limit our prayer in God and his holy will, asking abſolutely his glory, and our ſaluation: but remitting the meanes vnto his wiſedome and pleaſure. The fountaine of our heart muſt not powre foorth ſweet and ſowre together, praying, but with impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: let vs ſet him no time as the Diſciples did about the kingdome of Iſrael, but let vs come to the reſolution of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. <hi>Behold, here am I, let him doe to me as it ſeemeth good in his eyes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudi 8.</note> Worthy is the Oration of <hi>Iudith</hi> which ſhee made to her people of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> who would deliuer vp the Citie into the hands of the enemy, vnleſſe within few dayes the Lord ſhould helpe them: Who are you that haue temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lord, and ſet your ſelues in the place of God? Let vs waite for ſaluation from him, and call vpon him to helpe vs, and he will heare our voice if it pleaſe him; thus ſhould wee exhort our ſelues in our prayers, when impatience doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege our hearts. It is ſafe for vs to caſt the ankers of all our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180761:22"/>
purpoſes, and to ſtay our wils vpon his will. The reaſons to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> perſwade vs to bring it with vs, are three: the firſt is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the ſpirituall Phyſicians of Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. and in the prayer which he hath taught vs: of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 37.7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and of the reſt. The ſecond is, the Lords equity in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: he gouerneth not by luſt, but by law: hee draweth thee not to obedience by a violent chaine of his vnchangeable purpoſe, but by reaſon and iuſtice: eſteeme not his will in the moderating of the world as immoderate: hee hath a will, but not as inordinate Princes, who hauing the raines of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion giuen into their hands, doe many things inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without Law, Reaſon, Iuſtice, Equity: proclaiming with <hi>Nero,</hi> that they may doe all things, and that no body may controll them. No, no, beloued, his will is alwaies holy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies iuſt and equitable, although it ſeemeth vnto thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is the example of Chriſt; Chriſtians, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God it ſelfe, in whom the Deitie dwelt bodily, was content to forſake his wiſedome, and to be ordered and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by this ſquire of his Fathers will: <hi>Father, not my will, but thine be fulfilled.</hi> This is then the ſpirituall furniture which we muſt carry with vs, if wee will goe to the name of <hi>Iehouah.</hi> Prayer with theſe companions will returne laden with the ſheaues of comfort and bliſſe from the plentifulleſt fields. And by theſe it is manifeſted, that the righteous onely goe to this place: the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> is not like vnto the earthly places, vnto which in the time of infection reſort both good and bad. The vngodly may make a ſhew to goe into it, but yet they connot come thither, for there is the ſpirit of prayer, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. which is giuen onely to them that bring with them this ſpirituall furniture. As for weapons to ſafegard our ſelues, wee neede none, for this houſhold-ſtuffe are ſpirituall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. This ſhall ſuffice for the Arke of <hi>Noah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A truſty friend and ſeruant appointed by the Magiſtrate of heauen, to aide the ſicke in the time of Plague.</note>Now becauſe the Ciuill Magiſtrate appointeth in euery Pariſh truſtie men to aide the infected, and to prouide them with neceſſaries: Giue mee alſo leaue to ſhew vnto you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, a truſtie friend and ſeruant to ayde the ſicke, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Magiſtrate of heauen, If yee are deſirous to know
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:180761:22"/>
who it is, Prayer is his name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50 <hi>Call vpon mee &amp;c. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> hath vſed this faithfull friend in the time of the plague, he hath ſent it as an Embaſſadour into the Court of heauen to ſue for peace: he ſent not merites, diſtruſtfulneſſe, impatience, or blaſphemies: but prayer, the ſureſt and effectualleſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, happy for ſucceſſe. Wee are all deſirous, if the Lord viſite vs with the rod of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to haue ſome truſtie and faithfull friend or ſeruant to keepe and ayde vs, to diſpatch our buſineſſe, to ſend here and there, and to prouide vs with neceſſaries: and wee make much of ſuch that will aſſiſt vs in ſuch a fearefull ſickneſſe. Wee can haue no better ſeruant then King <hi>Dauids</hi> friend, who hath many good qualities: we deſire in the time of plague a ſeruant or friend,<note place="margin">1 Faithfull.</note> in whom wee finde theſe good qualities:<note place="margin">The qualities of this friend.</note> Firſt, <hi>Faithfulneſſe,</hi> for many haue beene robd by their keepers, as experience teacheth. Prayer is a meſſenger of eſpeciall truſt, it wil trauaile with vs by day: awake with vs by night: it will not forſake vs by land, by water, in weale, in woe, liuing or dying, it is our laſt friend and indiſſolubleſt companion. Secondly,<note place="margin">2 Quicke.</note> wee deſire one quick of ſpeed: Prayer is able in a minute to mount aboue the Eagles of the skie, into the heauen of heauens, and is a chariot of fire bearing vs aloft into the preſence of God to ſeeke his aſſiſtance; hee knoweth to addreſſe himſelfe in waies vnknowne in the ſtilleſt ſilence of the night, till he come to the ſecrets and chamber of the Lord, King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician. Thirdly, wee ſeeke one who is willing, and is not afraid,<note place="margin">3 Willing.</note> (for they are ſcarce to be found) prayer is ſuch a friend, he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to be with thee: neither the tediouſneſſe of the way, or difficultie of the paſſage can hinder him from his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4 Learned.</note> we are deſirous to haue one that can ſpeake lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which the Phyſician can vnderſtand, if need were to ſend him thither, and who can prouide vs of neceſſaries, ſuch one is prayer: for what language ſoeuer it ſpeaketh, the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of heauen can vnderſtand it.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, one that is able to comfort vs in our diſtreſſe,<note place="margin">5 A comforter.</note> ſuch a comforter is praier, it is the life of the ſoule: if thou art per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed with ſuch griefe of heart, as neither wine (according
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180761:23"/>
to the aduice of <hi>Salomon</hi>) nor ſtrong drink can bring eaſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſpirit melting like waxe, finding no comfort at all ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in light or darkeneſſe, pleaſures or riches, kinsfolkes or friends, wiſhing with <hi>Iob</hi> 4. <hi>O that thou wouldeſt hide mee in the graue, and keepe mee ſecret vntill thy wrath is paſt:</hi> yet then this friend is our comfort, hee will ſpeake for vs vnto the Lord, King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician, by this we may flie into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Gods mercies. <hi>If any then be afflicted amongſt you, let him pray, Iam.</hi> 5. The reaſon why we deſire a friend with all theſe qualities, is that he might both aide, and prouide vs with all neceſſaries: prayer is a friend who is able to diſpatch <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> all our buſineſſe. Deſireſt thou a Phyſitian in thy ſicknes to cure thee, ſend this friend praier to King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> dwelling in heauen, and he will bring him with him. If thou needeſt phyſicke to heale thee, and which is good for thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, ſend prayer into heauen to fetch the hearbe of patience, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which groweth not in our owne garden. If thou deſireſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for thy ſoule, ſend him to the Lord, he will fetch for thee, all that thou wanteſt, the bread of life, that heauenly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Manna, the bloud of Chriſt, the waters of mercy. Needeſt thou a comforter, ſend praier vnto the Lord, and he wil bring with him the beſt <hi>comforter</hi> of the ſicke, <hi>the holy Ghoſt, it is his name; Iohn</hi> 14. he will not feare to come to thee, as often the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> bodily Phyſician. Laſtly, if we deſire our friends to come and viſite vs, ſend prayer for them, and they will come: God the father, God the ſonne, God the holy Ghoſt. No friend then better then prayer. There are ſome bad ſeruants of which we muſt take heed, and as in the time of plague there are ſome bad ſeruants who robbe and bereaue the ſick of that he hath: ſo there are ſome wicked friends who will depriue vs of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comforts, if we be not ware of them. Firſt if we ſhould vſe the aide of <hi>merits</hi> and ſend them vp,<note place="margin">1 Bad ſeruants. Merites.</note> the ſtarres in heauen would diſdaine it, that wee which dwell at the footſtoole of God dare to preſume ſo farre, when the pureſt creatures in heauen are impure in his ſight.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6 4.</note> Secondly, if we ſend vp feare and diſtruſtfulneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Feare.</note> the length of the way will tire them out, they are as heauy and lumpiſh as gaddes of yron, they will
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180761:23"/>
ſinke to the ground, before they come halfe way to the throne of ſaluation. Thirdly, if we ſend vp blaſphemies and curſes,<note place="margin">3 Blaſphemies.</note> all the creatures betwixt heauen and earth will band themſelues againſt vs. The Sunne and Moone will raine downe bloud, the fire, hote burning coales, and the ayre thunderbolts vpon our heads. And therefore let vs not vſe the ayde of theſe three bad ſeruants. As prayer is a ſeruant to ayde the ſicke, ſo it is a truſtie friend or ſeruant to keepe your houſen, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. (O ye Londoners that are departed) in the Citie yee vſe the ayd and truſt of others, but they are not the beſt, for they are mortall and corruptible: exhort them therfore to vſe this friend towards the Lord, both for you &amp; for themſelues: for <hi>except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it: except the Lord keepe the citie, the keeper waiteth in vaine, ſaith Dauid.</hi> Thus I haue ſhewen you that be at <hi>London,</hi> beloued of God, called to be Saints, <hi>Salomons Peſthouſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 127.1.</note> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in with your families.</p>
            <p>I come now to you beloued that haue left your mother Citie for a time, which hope to returne:<note place="margin">An exerciſe for the Londoners that are in the Countrey.</note> your departure I will not diſprooue, nor wiſer then I, if ye haue vſed it lawfully, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring in your exile the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> And ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the time in thoſe things which make for the peace of your Citie. To refreſh your minds, and ſpend your time there becauſe the workes of your vocation you cannot exerciſe: diuers other exerciſes I know are vſed, perhaps not ſo well as ye might: all of them I doe not condemne: but it is to be feared, that the exerciſes of ſome haue been &amp; are friuolous, &amp; game ſome quarrellers, and that carding, dicing, and that <hi>Cup challenging Profeſſion,</hi> by which many drinking to health, drinke themſelues out of health, haue beene to others as vſuall paſtimes, as the fields to walke in. Giue me leaue beloued to ſhew you a better Exerciſe, and another paſtime, the paſtime of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> a royall exerciſe, which he vſed in the time of plague, his prayer and inuocation with the elders of Iſrael: ſpend herein your time beloued till ye returne: when your Mother mourneth, will you ſport? when the <hi>head</hi> ſmarteth, ſhall the <hi>members</hi> be ſenſeleſſe? pray with the Prophet for the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180761:24"/>
peace of your Ieruſalem. It is the Apoſtles precept, to pray continually, which if it euer was time to practiſe, it is at this preſent.<note place="margin">The praiſe of Prayer.</note> Suffer mee to enter into the praiſe of this exerciſe, diuers things doe adde commendation to it, which ought to perſwade you to the vſe thereof.<note place="margin">1 It is Diuine.</note> The firſt argument of praiſe may be taken from the author thereof Not <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Samuel,</hi> Prophet or Apoſtle, Patriarke or Martyr, but God the father, God the ſonne, God the holy Ghoſt, the bleſſed Trinitie haue beene the authors, which make it diuine and heauenly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.<note place="margin">2 Honourable.</note> The ſecond argument from the perſons which haue vſed it, we delight in Exerciſes which are accounted honorable, &amp; which men of credite and good account doe commonly vſe; this Exerciſe is honorable, yea royall: not baſe and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible onely haue ſpent their time with it, but Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, King <hi>Dauid, Manaſſes, Ezechiah,</hi> and the reſt. The bleſſed Prophets, Patriarks, yea the Prince of glory, the ſonne of the immortall God Chriſt Ieſus: It is ſo heauenly and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that by prayer we doe approach neere vnto God, and doe as it were conioyne our ſelues with him: while we are in the body, we are abſent from home: but by prayer we doe aſcend into heauen, prayer being as it were the band of our internall coniunction with God. Further, it is honourable, not only in regard of the perſons which haue vſed it, but alſo, to God and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vs. To God, for thereby we honor and glorifie him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. acknowledging that all might, glory, felicity, health and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation belongeth to him, and that from him alone we muſt receiue it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> To vs, for thereby we are familiar with the Lord: if it be an honor for vs to be familiar with earthly Princes, which are but duſt and aſhes, O what an honour is it then to be familiar with the King of Kings, and Monarke of the world! It is the chiefeſt honour whereunto he can aduance vs, when hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>prayer.</hi> If we deſire the valour of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, by prayer wee may ſtand in place where Gods hand hath made a breach, and doe as much as all the chariots and horſemen in a kingdome. If you eſteeme it an honour to be in the ſeruice of the Prince, giue your ſelfe to prayer, it is one of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180761:24"/>
the chiefeſt parts of Gods ſeruice. Yea it is ſo excellent, that the ſacrifice of praier is offered alone to him,<note place="margin">Chriſtian.</note> whom <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth excellent and glorious. It is an honor to be a chriſtian, let vs therefore vſe the chriſtian exerciſe: two things doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh vs, our name, and the example of Chriſt: Chriſtians <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we are called, annointed alſo to be Prieſts and Prophets, and that royall Prieſthood in Chriſt Ieſus. As the Prieſts offered <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſacrifices of bullocks and rammes, ſo let vs offer the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayer, which hath alſo beene Chriſts exerciſe. Mercy hath praied, and ſhall not miſerie? Charitie hath praied, and ſhall not iniquity pray? the Phyſician proſtrated vpon the ground praieth, and ſhall not the ſicke and the patient call vpon the Lord? the innocent, and he in whoſe mouth there is no fraud praieth, and ſhall not the ſinner? the Iudge prayeth, and deſireth that the Lord would be mercifull and ſpare his people, and ſhall not the guiltie bee ſuppliant to receiue mercie?</p>
            <p>The pleaſure of it,<note place="margin">3 Delectable.</note> may bee the third argument of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: this exerciſe is pleaſant and delectable. To ſpend the time in the Country, diuers vſe pleaſant and delectable Exerciſes: this is both acceptable to God, and pleaſant to man: to God, for the ſweet odours of our prayers aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">1 To God.</note> And as the ſent of incenſe &amp; Odoriferous things is pleaſant to the noſtrils of mortall man: So <hi>the prayer of the righteous,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome, is pleaſant to the immortall God.</hi> It is not then, the lamentation of men, eiulation of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children, mingling heauen and earth together with a confuſion of out-cries, that is acceptable to God, and which can enforce him to giue vs audience. but it is humble prayer, the voyce of repentance: which as <hi>Ieſus Syrach</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 35.16. ſhall bee accepted with fauour,<note place="margin">2 To man.</note> and reach vnto the cloudes. Secondly, to vs, all that our heart deſireth is in this Exerciſe. Some being in the Countrey, ſpend their time in diſcourſes, prayer is a diſcourſe with our beloued. If it was a pleaſure to <hi>Iacob</hi> to ſpeake vnto <hi>Rachel,</hi> and to <hi>Ionathan</hi> with <hi>Dauid:</hi> O what a recreation is it for our ſoules that they may familiarly ſpeake with him, whoſe loue vnto vs is better then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180761:25"/>
gold or pearle. If wee delight to ſpeake languages, by prayer wee may ſpeake the excellenteſt language which hath euer beene, the language of Canaan: let vs not feare to diſcourſe with the Lord by our prayers, for hee is not like vnto the ſpruce and finicall ſonnes of men: feare not, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> he ſeeketh not at thy hands painted eloquence, an angelicall tongue, filed phraſes: but beholdeth only the beauty of thy ſoule. Others take their pleaſure while they are in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to ride vp and downe in their Coaches and Chariots, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried therein betwixt heauen and earth. Let prayer bee your Coach beloued: it is as one ſaith, as a Chariot of fire, bearing vs aloft in the preſence of God, able to mount vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Eagles of the skie to ſeeke the Lords aſſiſtance. In the time of plague, there was heretofore appointed a Waggon or Coach to carry the ſicke to the Peſt-houſe, &amp; there to bee healed: there is no better Chariot to carry our ſoules vnto the houſe of heauen to bee healed by that heauenly Phyſician, then humble prayer. Some delight to goe vp and down and ſee their friends; our beſtfriends at this time, &amp; at altimes who can do vs the moſt good: are God the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt: let vs viſite them therefore continually by our prayers. Others in writing letters, what is prayer elſe but as it were a letter ſent to God in which wee declare our neede: and as a letter is an amiable diſcourſe and conference of one friend with another, as if they were both preſent: So is our prayer, as a friendly letter or diſcourſe of vs which are abſent from home: with our beſtfriend the Lord, as if wee were preſent with him in heauen. Send this letter, and letter vpon letter: yee that are now exiled, ſhew vnto the Lord your need: pray vnto him that hee will bring you home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and remooue that in his mercy which keepeth you backe. Laſtly, ſome in running of Races, or in Hunting: but yee beloued in this afflicted time, runne the way of Gods Commandements: as <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>runne to the name of Iehouah with the righteous, Prou.</hi> 18. <hi>runne the race which is ſet before you, and that with patience, looking vnto Chriſt Ieſus, Hebr.</hi> 12.1. and ſo runne that yee may obtaine that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180761:25"/>
which you ſue for. Hunt not after the pleaſures of this life, but after the liuing God: and <hi>as the Hart brayeth for the riuers of waters, ſo let your ſoules pant after the liuing God, Pſal.</hi> 42.1. That the Lords <hi>Hunter, Pſal.</hi> 91. hunt vs not, but that <hi>the Lord may deliver vs from the ſnare of the Hunter, and from the noyſome peſtilence, Pſalme</hi> 91.3. Vſe therefore this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exerciſe: the childe is neuer better but when it is in his fathers and mothers lap: So ſhall you neuer be better, but when by prayer you creepe as it were in your heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers boſome: it will kindle your loue toward him, as the loue of louers is kindled, the more they come together: and if yee remaine there the next enſuing Winter, feruent prayer will bee in ſtead of fire, to kindle in your hearts the loue of God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the profit of this Exerciſe commendeth it much;<note place="margin">4 Profitable.</note> it is not onely delectable, but alſo profitable. Some which are in the Countrey at this time ſpend their time I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe profitably,<note place="margin">1 To vs.</note> riding vp and downe to buy commodities againſt the future: but prayer is a farre profitabler Exerciſe for this time, for it is not onely profitable to our ſelues, but alſo vnto others: yea, to the whole Realme. And as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh of Godlineſſe, that it is profitable for al things; ſo I may ſay of prayer, that it can obtaine any thing: profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vs in two reſpects: Firſt, to obtaine that we haue not: Secondly, to keepe that we haue obtained Firſt, <hi>if thou lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> knowledge and wiſedome,</hi> prayer is the meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, <hi>Iames</hi> I. <hi>If thy vnderſtanding bee darke, pray with Dauid, Pſalm.</hi> 119. <hi>Open mine eyes O Lord, that I may ſee the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of thy Law.</hi> If thou lackeſt zeale, pray with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Lord incline my heart vnto thy law, &amp;c.</hi> And becauſe this world is a deſart where we may eaſily erre, pray with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>Leade me in thy pathes, &amp;c.</hi> If our ſoules be infected with the plague of vanitie and couetouſneſſe, the meanes to remooue it, is prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>O Lord remooue farre from me vanitie, and encline not my heart to couetouſneſſe.</hi> The meanes to obtaine a contented minde, is alſo prayer, <hi>Prou.</hi> 30. <hi>Pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor riches giue mee not, &amp;c.</hi> If thou deſireſt to thinke vpon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180761:26"/>
thy mortalitie, by the ſubiect which now is preſented to thee, pray with <hi>Dauid. Pſa.</hi> 90. <hi>Teach vs O Lord, to number our dayes, that wee may apply our hearts to wiſedome.</hi> If yee deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, it is not your ſports and delights, but your praiers that muſt bring you backe.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> If yee deſire the ceaſing of the begun plague, it is your prayer that muſt remooue the cauſe, that the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> effect may ceaſe. As praier obtaineth, ſo it keepeth that you haue already obtained: ſuch are not your Exerciſes, which ye your ſelues haue inuented, O ſonnes of <hi>Adam:</hi> for by them you often looſe that which you had purchaſed ryotouſly (which <hi>Alexander</hi> blamed in his friends) waſting and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming your whole ability.<note place="margin">2 The others.</note> There is another thing which ought to perſwade you to this Exerciſe: which is, that it is profitable to others prayer doth more good then Almes: for by our Almes we can helpe but a few; but by our prayers wee can helpe thouſands and thouſands: yea thoſe which are farre off. Prayers, are the almes of the rich as well as of the poore: for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did as well begge for prayers, as poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> for crummes. Yee rich men that are in the Countrey, beſtow theſe almes vpon the poore, as well as the almes of your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and in this afflicted time, ſeeke more to profite the whole Realme by your prayers, then by your commodities. I end this point with the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine: Plus profeci orando qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> legendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 To ſtrengthen vs.</note> 
               <hi>I haue more profited by praying, than by reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, this Exerciſe is commendable, becauſe it is able to ſtrengthen vs. Some in the Countrey doe ſpend their time in Exerciſes, by which they may maintaine their health, and ſtrengthen their bodies, that they may bee able to doe any thing: the Exerciſe of praier is good to make vs recouer the health of our ſoules, which was waxen weake: as this preſent begun plague, and your preſent exile both doe witneſſe. Yea, it is able to make vs doe admirable things. Was it euer heard that mightie Potentates, as there haue beene many: <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great, <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> and the reſt, could make the Sunne or the Moone to ſtand ſtill in the firmament? And yet this hath done the praier of <hi>Ioſuah.</hi> Haue there euer beene any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſo great and mightie, which could make the Earth to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180761:26"/>
tremble vnder their feet? No beloued: the mightie armie of <hi>Xerxes</hi> could not doe it, and yet this hath done the praier of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. Who hath euer heard that it hath been poſſible to mortall man, to raiſe the dead and to giue life to the deceaſed? The Phyſicians doe acknowledge their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, and yet this hath done the praier of <hi>Elizaeus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> As the Apoſtle then in the commendation of faith, rehearſeth the wonders which they haue wrought by faith: So it may bee ſaid of praier which is done in faith: by praier <hi>Moſes</hi> diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the red re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: by praier <hi>Ioſua</hi> beat down the wals of <hi>Iericho:</hi> by praier <hi>Sidrach</hi> and <hi>Abednago</hi> quenched the fire: <hi>Daniel</hi> ſtopped the Lyons greedie and deuouring throates: the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles opened the priſons and brake their bands. And I will yet adde one thing, by praier, brethren, you ſhall be able to ouercome him, who is inuincible. The Lord hath beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and beguirt your Citie by his deſtroying Angell, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes to reſiſt him, and to make him retire, are your humble praiers: O the admirable force of praier, which ouercommeth him who ouercommeth al things! I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the praiers of the righteous to the haires of <hi>Sampſon:</hi> as long as his head was adorned and couered with them, hee was in a manner inuincible, hee brake the cordes and roapes wherewith he was bound: his ſtrength lying in his haire; but being ſhauen, his ſtrength went from him, he waxed weake and like other men. All your ſtrength beloued lieth in your praier, as long as you exerciſe your ſelues therein, you ſhall be able to reſiſt, I ſay not the tyrants &amp; the deuil, but the Lords Angel himſelfe. You haue another enemie, the which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, it is neceſſarie that you learn to handle the ſword of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, this enemie is cruell, malicious, mightie, ſubtile and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, his name bewrayeth his nature; Sathan by name, who is not only in the Citie, but followeth you in the country (for as a deuouring Lyon he compaſſeth the earth) and there he ſeeketh to make you forget the Lord, and the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> to ſticke to the creature, &amp; forget the Creator; to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Enemie and his fierie darts, let this be your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Exerciſe: Imitate the induſtrious wreſtlers, who to eaſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180761:27"/>
downe another, firſt fall downe themſelues: ſo to ouerthrow this enemy who ſeeketh in the Countrey to ouerthrow you; caſt downe your ſelues by humble prayer and faſting, that in that place you may triumph ouer him who thought to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer you. To end beloued, to you all I ſpeake together, you that are in the Citie, enter this Towre: you that are caſt downe vpon your beddes, vſe the aide of this friend: you that are departed, let this be your paſtime, that we altogether may be preſerued from the deluge, and the waters may decreaſe more and more, till they be dried vp, that being decreaſed we may offer the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing, as <hi>Noah</hi> offered vnto the Lord after the floud. But let vs not be like vnto the ſea-ſicke, who onely are weake, lament and cry as long as they are in the tempeſt, and when they begin to ſmell the ayre, and are gone out of the ſhip, they forget both their ſickneſſe and their deliuerance.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But rather as <hi>Iacob</hi> (ye that are departed) flying to heauen, the remembrance of his countrey being ſweet, made an excellent vow and prayer, that if hee came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his fathers houſe in ſafetie, the Lord ſhould be his God, and that he would giue vnto the Lord the tenth of all he had: ſo likewiſe ye that are departed, or to depart from your Mother Citie, as <hi>Iacob</hi> from his fathers houſe, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof being ſweet to you, as I know it is, make the vow and prayer of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that when the Lord bring you home againe in ſafety, that hee ſhall be your God, and that yee will ſerue him with more zeale and feruencie then ye haue done before: further that ye will (if not the tenth) yet ſome part of your goods, beſtow vpon the Lord, in his poore members. Let the Apoſtles words be the concluſion,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Yee therefore belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware leſt ye be alſo lead away with the errour of the wicked, but grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt; to him be glory both now and for euermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:180761:27"/>
               <head>A zealous Prayer in time of the Plague to be vſed by all <hi>Londoners</hi> that are fled from the Citie, and all others that are ſenſible of the Cities Calamitie, whereſoeuer.</head>
               <p>O LORD GOD, our onely helper and Defender, who amongſt all other Euils, haſt promiſed to <hi>deliuer thy People from the noyſome Peſtilence;</hi> Wee beſeech thee, take this thy heauy Plague away from vs; and eſpecially with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy hand from off the Citie of <hi>LONDON,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis of this Kingdome, where thy Name is daily called vpon. And let our humble Supplications (which at this time, vpon our knees wee make vnto thee in the name of CHRIST IESVS,) procure our happy Releaſe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe thy Wrath, which wee haue iuſtly procured againſt vs through ſinne. Lord, we being heartily ſorry for our ſinnes, (fully purpoſing by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit to amend our liues) doe humbly intreat thee to haue mercy vpon vs, to take away this plague from vs, and not to ſuffer vs to periſh after ſo miſerable a ſort. We thanke thee, O Lord, that thou haſt not left vs altogether comfortleſſe, nor caſt vs off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope, but haſt ſomewhat withdrawne thy heauy hand, and ſpared many of vs; we pray thee to continue thy fauour daily more and more towards vs; to deale with vs in Mercy, not in Iuſtice; to bleſſe vs and all thoſe that depend on vs; To ſet thy ſauing Marke vpon our houſes, as thou diddeſt for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> To giue order to the <hi>Deſtroyer,</hi> that <hi>he hurt vs not,</hi> to put thy ſtrength to our Medicines; to let thy good bleſſing make the preſeruatiues of Phyſicians effectuall; and to make our ſhifting places, for more ſecuritie, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto vs. Giue vs grace, O Lord, not to truſt too much on outward meanes, but onely on thy Mercy. Protect vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180761:28"/>
in all our waies; haue pittie vpon our diſtreſſed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters, whether in <hi>London</hi> or elſe where, Comfort the deſolate Widow; prouide for all Orphanes and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Children; gather vs together againe, that by theſe meanes are diſperſed: Send vs Health, Peace with men vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and peace of Conſcience towards thee, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:28"/>
            <head>In the Viſitation, Anno 1603. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Holland,</hi> (of pious memorie) pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a booke entituled <hi>Spirituall Preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues againſt the Peſtilence:</hi> Whereunto was annexed <hi>An Admonition concerning the vſe of Phyſick,</hi> and all naturall helpes, which the Lord may bleſſe for our good, as in other maladies, ſo in the Peſtilence.</head>
            <head type="sub">Which booke being worne out of Print, the Admontion is here added, for the vſe and benefit of vs now liuing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Iames</hi> addeth that after the former ſpirituall comforts the Elders of his time, <hi>did annoint the ſicke with oyle of the name of the Lord,</hi> euen as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour had before appointed, and his Diſciples practiſed in their miraculous cures.<note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The gift of healing the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.30. Shewing it to be a peculiar gift: <hi>are all doers of miracles? haue all the gifts of healing?</hi> And it ceaſſed in the Church, when the Goſpell was ſufficiently confirmed with miracles, euen anon after the Apoſtles, Prophets and Euangeliſts had finiſhed and ended their worke, and when their time was expired.</p>
            <p>Now then the gift ceaſſing: it is madneſſe to retaine ſtill the time which went with the gift, that is, this annointing or aneiling and more madneſſe to make a Sacrament of it, as Antichriſt hath done, &amp; moſt extreame madnes to giue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them only which are a dying, which was wont to be giuen
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:180761:29"/>
to ſuch as did recouer health againe. Wherefore as the holy <hi>Viſitors</hi> did then firſt vſe their ſpirituall exerciſe, which is left for vs to practiſe, and next this extraordinary gift and meanes of healing: ſo let vs carefully and wiſely heere call for, in the ſecond place, the learned Phyſician, the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ordinary meanes which God hath left vnto vs in nature as long as the World endureth: This order that holy Writer,<note place="margin">Ecclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 38.9.10 11.12.</note> the Godly Preacher commendeth vnto vs in theſe words; <hi>My ſonne, faile not in thy ſickneſſe, but pray vnto the Lord and he will make thee whole: leaue off from ſinne, and order thine hands aright, &amp;c. and cleanſe thine heart from all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. Then giue place to the Phyſician, for the Lord hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, let him not goe from thee, for thou haſt neede of him: the houre may come that their enterpriſes may haue good ſucceſſe, for he alſo ſhall pray vnto the Lord, that he would proſper that which is giuen for the prolonging of life. Whereas ſome obiect, that</hi> in the Peſtilence naturall remedies <hi>of Phyſick cannot benefit vs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the cauſes here <hi>cannot be ſeene or found in nature:</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with M.B. <hi>If there come into the Peſtilence no naturall cauſes, then theſe whom the Plague hath infected, cannot doubtleſſe ſo much be eaſed, much leſſe be healed, by naturall remedies.</hi> But this ſecond to be very falſe experience and common ſenſe do dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell vs. Wherefore I affirme that naturall remedies muſt not be neglected.</p>
            <p>Againe, whereas others doe obiect, that <hi>Phyſick heere often is ſeene to haue but ſmall good ſucceſſe:</hi> I anſwere, that wee muſt not ſay of naturall Preſeruatiues, that becauſe they doe not benefit one, or two, or three: therefore they cannot helpe any at all. It is a bad concluſion: for, conſider that God doth gouerne naturall cauſes and their effects as it pleaſeth him, and bleſſeth them to whom hee will, where, and when he will. And hence it commeth, that the infection toucheth not euery one that is in danger of it, neither is it deadly to euery one that is infected.</p>
            <p>Others yet more fondly diſpute againſt naturall remedies in this ſickneſſe: and they ſay that <hi>God hath here a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall prouidence, and he will ſmite whom he will to death, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180761:29"/>
all remedies are to ſmall purpoſe.</hi> Theſe men againe want iudgement.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that the Lord no doubt when he ſent a Famine into Egypt, and the Regions thereabout, he determined who ſhould die in that Scarcity: yet for all this, ceaſeth not <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with moſt wiſe counſell to prouide for the Egyptians, and <hi>Iacob</hi> for his familie. The like did <hi>Paul</hi> in the Sea with the Mariners, when he had receiued an anſwer, he ſhould come to Rome ſafely.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt knew his time, and yet hee went aſide often from his enemies hand till his houre came, vſing the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meanes for his preſeruation.</p>
            <p>And that no man may ſtand ſtifly in his owne raſh iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Quid Temeritate fortius?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tully) What ſo foole-hardie, or ſo violent, as raſh and haſtie ſpirits?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. De natum deorum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Heare what that learned Father, (of euer bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith of this matter in his<note n="*" place="margin">De Peſte in Wittebergs. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1527.</note> Treatiſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of Dutch into Latine, and in Engliſh thus much;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God hath created Phyſicke, and giuen vs a minde and reaſon, that euery man ſhould haue a care of his owne body for health and life: whoſoeuer will not vſe theſe, when as without the hurt of his neighbour hee may, the ſame man betrayeth his owne life, and there lacketh little, but that before God he is made a murtherer: for by the ſame reaſon hee may deſpiſe meat and drinke, rayment and houſing, &amp; truſting too much vnto his faith ſay, if God will, he can preſerue me without all theſe things: than the which folly, this is yet greater, that he which after this ſort, casteth off the care of his body, he may hurt and infect others alſo, and ſo through his negligence, he may purchaſe the blame of a murderer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some men indeed doe as fooliſh men doe in a common firing, which will not come and helpe the Citie, but let the fire alone, that the whole Citie might be burned: namely vpon this truſt, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if God will, he can without water quench the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, friend, thou oughteſt in no wiſe ſo to deale: Nay, it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and ſhameful which thou perſwadeſt thy ſelf but rather vſe remedies and Medicines, and do whatſoeuer any way may helpe: perfume thine houſe, orchard or ſtreet: flie the infected places, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180761:30"/>
ſo behaue thy selfe as one willing to quench not to maintaine this open fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe it followeth in the ſame Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Sathan by the will of God, either by himſelfe or his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, hath wrought vs this deadly Infection; I on the other ſide before all things will pray vnto God, that of his mercy he will take away the ſame from vs: then I will put to my ſimple helping hand, both by perfuming and cleanſing of the ayre, by vſing of medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and alſo in ſhunning the infection, where my preſence is not neceſſarie. Leſt I might ſeeme my ſelfe to haue neglected ſome thing, or to be cauſe of death vnto others, who through my negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence may take harme. But if God neuertheleſſe will haue mee viſited with this ſickneſſe or call me out of this world vnto his Kingdome, yet I haue not done but that which was my dutie; neither haue I offended in any thing, either againſt my ſelfe or my neighbour, but where my ſeruice is needfull, there I will let paſſe nothing of all things which either can or ought to be done of me. Behold this is that Godly faith indeed which doth nothing raſhly, neither tempteth God in any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then I conclude, when thou ſhalt haue wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and diſcerned the cauſes of the Peſtilence: then turn to God (as the Prophet biddeth) <hi>with all thine heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioal. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>with faſting, with weeping, and with mourning,</hi> and flee a loft by faith into the ſecret place, almightie ſhadow, and bleſſed protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord, and there reſt patiently as vnder his holy wings, euer praying for the increaſe of faith and patience, that thou mayſt quietly waite and depend vpon God and for a good Conſcience, that ſo thou maiſt auoide falſe, fooliſh, and wicked feares, and cheerefully ſtand in thy place: and carefully call for the Protection of the mighty, bleſſed and holy Angels, and for the communion and preſence of Ieſus Chriſt: ſo ſhalt thou chaſe far away the wicked and vncleane Spirits, which are ſent of God to poyſen and deſtroy men with the Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, when thou haſt vſed all the meanes before ſhewed for thy ſpirituall comfort and helpe, thou muſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect no ordinance nor helpe of God in nature, both for thy cure and preſeruation. The wicked, indeed, inuert and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:180761:30"/>
this order, as did <hi>Aſa,</hi> and therefore no meruell if they receiue often a curſe inſteed of a bleſſing; for if Phyſicke giue them health of body, their ſoules notwithſtanding are neuer cured or made any better by their chaſticements: but they daily gather more ſtrength to commit ſinne with boldneſſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>LEt the Rich ſeeke for the Godly, wiſe and learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and take heede of wicked ignorant bold Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks, which kill many men, and yet feare nothing, becauſe they be not called to their accompts, according to good Lawes for this cauſe prouided.</p>
               <p>And let the poorer ſort with good aduiſe and counſell (if they can haue any) vſe Maiſter <hi>Phaers</hi> medicines, in his ſhort, but learned Treatiſe of the Peſtilence, which hee wrote of purpoſe for the benefit and comfort of the Poore.</p>
               <p>I haue added a few medicines of Maſter <hi>Phaers,</hi> which may ſerue at a need, and by Gods grace do ſome good, when better counſell is wanting.</p>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A moſt precious Electuary againſt the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence for the Rich.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Cynamome elect,</hi> one ounce, <hi>Terra ſigillata,</hi> 6. drams, fine <hi>Mirre</hi> 3. drams, <hi>Vnicorns horne,</hi> one dram, <hi>the ſeed and rind of Citron, roots of Dyptany, Burnet, Tormentille, Zedoary, red Corall, ana:</hi> drams two, yellow <hi>Sannders,</hi> 4. ſcruples, red <hi>Saunders</hi> 2. ſcruples, <hi>White bene,</hi> and red <hi>Flowers of Marygolds, ana,</hi> one dram, <hi>Iuoryarced, Scabious, Betonice, Offininis tunicae appellatae, ſeed of Baſile, the bone of a Stags Heart, Saffron, ana,</hi> two ſcruples, make a fine powder, and ad vnto it of <hi>Bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniake Breparate</hi> two ounces, <hi>White ſugar,</hi> three pound, and with a <hi>Syrup of Acetociate Citri,</hi> make a goodly Electuary, and keepe it in a Glaſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Or this forme with leſſe coſt and quantitie.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of <hi>Dictamu, tormentil, bole armonick, Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> (that is, waſhed with water of <hi>Sabious) Terra figillata,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180761:31"/>
ana,</hi> 6. drams of the <hi>root of Gentian,</hi> and of <hi>the root of butter-burre,</hi> of <hi>Betonie,</hi> called in the ſhops <hi>Betonice tunica. Ana,</hi> 2. ſcruples, <hi>red Sanders</hi> one ſcruple, <hi>Inorie raced,</hi> the <hi>barke of Citron,</hi> of <hi>red Corall,</hi> of the <hi>bone of a Stags heart,</hi> of tho <hi>root of Zedoary, ana,</hi> halfe a dram of moſt <hi>pure Pearles,</hi> of both kinds of <hi>been, ana,</hi> 2. ſcruples, <hi>Fragmentorum quinque lapidum pretioſorum, ana,</hi> one ſcruple, <hi>Amber, good Vnicornes horne, ana,</hi> halfe a ſcruple, of <hi>Gold, and Siluer leaues</hi> three of each; min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle all theſe and make a fine powder.</p>
                  <p>If the Peſtilence come with great exceſſe of heat, take one dram and drinke it vp in Roſe water and Vineger; but if you feele it cold, take it in a draught of White Wine and couer you with clothes, ſo that you may ſweat as long as is poſſible, for without doubt it is a preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, as I my ſelfe haue oftentimes proued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Poore the beſt I find is this.</head>
                  <p>TAke the root called <hi>Petaſites</hi> in Latine, in Engliſh <hi>Butter-burre,</hi> growing by the water-ſide, drie it and make fine powder of it, and giue it the ſicke.</p>
                  <p>If the Peſtilence commeth with heat, take 3. drams of it in Roſe-water and Vineger: but if it come with a cold, giue it in a draught of Wine, and cauſe the partie to ſweat as long as he or ſhe can well endure it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>If a Botch appeare, to ripen it.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Mallowes,</hi> and the <hi>roots of Holyhoke,</hi> and <hi>Onions,</hi> as much as ſhall ſuffice, waſh them and ſeeth them in water, and afterward bray them in a Morter with <hi>powder of Linſeed, Fenugreke,</hi> and a good quantitie of <hi>Swines greaſe</hi> freſh, laying on the plaiſter euery day once.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To breake the Botch.</head>
                  <p>SOme lay on it a Plaiſter made of <hi>Figgee</hi> (which was King <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> plaſter, and therefore not to be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) adde <hi>ſowre leauen,</hi> and <hi>Raiſins without Kernels,</hi> brayed and incorporate altogether in <hi>oyle of Camomill.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:180761:31"/>
                  <head>To mundifie the Botch.</head>
                  <p>AFterward, mundifie the ſore with a ſalue made of <hi>yolkes of Egges, fine Barley flower,</hi> and a little <hi>Honey</hi> or <hi>oyle of Roſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For incarnation of the place.</head>
                  <p>LAſt of all for the perfect incarnation, Take the <hi>iuice of Daiſes,</hi> and with a little <hi>waxe</hi> make a ſoft ointment and vſe it, or you may lay thereto an other ſalue incarnatiue, as yee are wont to doe in other cleane ſores.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:180761:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LONDON, LOOK-BACKE.</hi> The Deſcription of the late great memorable and prodigious Plague. <hi>1625.</hi> ⸪</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOod God! what poiſon lurkd in that firſt fruict</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſurfet left vs wretches proſtitute</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a world of ſorrow? Not confin'd</l>
                  <l>Onely to teare and cruciate the minde</l>
                  <l>With ſad remembrance of the bliſſe, wherein</l>
                  <l>We might haue liu'd, but ſee the cruell Sin</l>
                  <l>Spares not our ſoules weake houſes, both doth ſpred</l>
                  <l>From viler parts vnto the nobler head</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Maladies, which now alas</l>
                  <l>Through each ſmall In-let of the Bodie, paſſe</l>
                  <l>Remorſleſſe Enemies, and batter downe,</l>
                  <l>The clayie bulwarkes of our Mud-wall'd towne.</l>
                  <l>Our throat is like that vaſt breach, which doth bring</l>
                  <l>In like the <hi>Troian</hi> Horſe dire ſurfetting;</l>
                  <l>When in the Stomach like the Market-place</l>
                  <l>The foes let looſe dare ſpred themſelues, and trace</l>
                  <l>Through all the Citie, ſome are ready firſt</l>
                  <l>To breake the Sluces, which doe raging burſt</l>
                  <l>And drowne low buildings, ſome with flaming brands</l>
                  <l>Fire holy Temples, ſome with Swords in hands</l>
                  <l>Sharpe-pointed-Iauelins, Malls, and poiſonous darts</l>
                  <l>Make Maſſacres through all the trembling parts</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:180761:32"/>Of the diſtreſſed Fabricke; no controll</l>
                  <l>Can barre'em but they will aſſault the Soule</l>
                  <l>It ſelfe almoſt, while each ſmall-breathing Pore</l>
                  <l>Betrayes vnto the foe a Poſterne Dore</l>
                  <l>To enter in at, euery crawling veyne</l>
                  <l>Affords him harbour, and doth Entertaine</l>
                  <l>The bloudie Enemie, each Muſcle, Nerue,</l>
                  <l>And Filme makes him a Fortreſſe to preſerue</l>
                  <l>His longer Durance, till the gueſt at laſt</l>
                  <l>With ruine payes his Hoſt for all that's paſt.</l>
                  <l>How many ſuch foes, thinke you? ſecret lye</l>
                  <l>When hundreds of them ambuſh in one Eye?</l>
                  <l>Which is the Lanthorne, and the Watch, and Light</l>
                  <l>Keepes Centurie for all the Bodies Night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As ſoone may I exactly number all</l>
                  <l>The fainting leaues that in an Autumne fall,</l>
                  <l>The Creatures of the Summer, or the Store</l>
                  <l>Of wilder inſects, which old <hi>Nilus</hi> ſhore</l>
                  <l>Each yeare produceth, as with Iudgement ſhow</l>
                  <l>How many fierce and bold diſeaſes flow</l>
                  <l>Vpon this wretched Carkaſſe, when each yeare</l>
                  <l>New troupes of raging Feuers domineere</l>
                  <l>That know no name, Each boy can nigh expreſſe</l>
                  <l>Diſeaſes now to Poſe <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Happy that age of gold, not onely cauſe</l>
                  <l>It had no vice, and ſo no need of Lawes,</l>
                  <l>When Nature was their <hi>Solon,</hi> and the want</l>
                  <l>Of Knowledge to doe ill, did make them Ignorant</l>
                  <l>Of the Redreſſe, not bleſs'd alone in this,</l>
                  <l>Although the ayre and earth increas'd their bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>But that an able Bodie was combin'd</l>
                  <l>In a ſweet friendſhip with a harmeleſſe mind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:180761:33"/>They knew no Phyſicke (though their drugs did grow</l>
                  <l>Then in full vertue, able to beſtow</l>
                  <l>Health on this age) becauſe they Knew not how</l>
                  <l>To get thoſe Sickneſſes, which men Know now.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ague</hi> with a hundred names; the <hi>Aches</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More than the Ioynts; the <hi>Palſey</hi> that attaches</l>
                  <l>The limbes with Diſſolution; the wild</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Bedlem Phrenſie,</hi> the <hi>Vertigo</hi> ſtil'd,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it whirles the giddie braines about:</l>
                  <l>The ſweving <hi>Megrim;</hi> and the racking <hi>Gout:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The cruell <hi>Stone;</hi> the torturing <hi>Collicke</hi> fierce</l>
                  <l>And wringing winds, which through the lims diſperſe</l>
                  <l>Their ayrie torments; lingring diſpence</l>
                  <l>Of pale <hi>Conſumptions,</hi> which beſot the ſenſe:</l>
                  <l>The Deluge of a <hi>Dropſie.</hi> When ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Run through'em all? the ſleepie <hi>Lethargie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quick-murdering <hi>Apoplexie</hi> which doth Kill</l>
                  <l>E're it makes Sicke: the piteous <hi>Falling-Ill:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Elephant-skin'd <hi>Leproſie: Iaundies</hi> ſtaine:</l>
                  <l>Ambuſh'd <hi>Impoſtumes</hi> which ſurprize the braine:</l>
                  <l>With hart aſſaulting <hi>Pleuriſies:</hi> the tough</l>
                  <l>And cluttered <hi>Flegme:</hi> and <hi>Rheume</hi> that breeds the <hi>Cough,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strappado,</hi> Gramps; the ſodaine-pricking <hi>Stitch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Night-mare:</hi> which the people thinke a Witch,</l>
                  <l>Th'all conquering <hi>Pox,</hi> to which compar'd the reſt</l>
                  <l>Are Lady Sick-fits: this is that forraine gueſt</l>
                  <l>The Diuell-inſtructed <hi>Indies</hi> to vs ſold</l>
                  <l>To recompence the filching of their Gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All theſe and more innumerable powers</l>
                  <l>Lay ſiege vnto this weake-wall'd Fort of ours</l>
                  <l>And oft ſurprize an Out-work, yea ſometime</l>
                  <l>In deſperate malice ready are to clime</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:180761:33"/>The walls themſelues: till that the heart, much like</l>
                  <l>A ſtrong Defendant, maketh good the Dike</l>
                  <l>And giues'em a repulſe: yet oft, alas,</l>
                  <l>This noble Champion ſtaines the conquer'd Maſſe</l>
                  <l>With dying blood: For Sickneſſe is a Fight,</l>
                  <l>The victory doubtfull, Chances infinite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But hath that power who is all Mercy, ſtill</l>
                  <l>More, and more cruell Puniſhments to Kill</l>
                  <l>Minute liu'd man? yea, though you adde to theſe</l>
                  <l>Pale meager Famine, Murders of the Seas,</l>
                  <l>And Warres vaſt Slaughters; you ſhall find one more</l>
                  <l>That may affright the reſt we nam'd before</l>
                  <l>The <hi>PLAGVE,</hi> whoſe very naming ſeemes t'affright</l>
                  <l>My trembling Quill, as it doth haſt to write,</l>
                  <l>Leſt as it raging flies about the land</l>
                  <l>This Inſtant it might ſeaze vpon my hand:</l>
                  <l>The Plague a dreary Puniſhment, Heauens curſe,</l>
                  <l>The fatall Engine of Deſtruction, worſe</l>
                  <l>Than we can well imagine, which doth bring</l>
                  <l>Terrour on mortals, Death on euery thing,</l>
                  <l>And Deſolation vnto Cities: O</l>
                  <l>What ere thou art, dire Ill, whether thou doeſt flow</l>
                  <l>From powerfull Influence of the Starres, or rather</l>
                  <l>Doeſt thy vaſt malice and contagion gather</l>
                  <l>From poiſonous Southerne windes, which haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail'd</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſickly ayre, or Steames Exhal'd</l>
                  <l>From th'Earths enuenom'd wombe: or whether't bee</l>
                  <l>Our Bodies Conſtitutions, which agree</l>
                  <l>With the malicious ayre and ſo contract</l>
                  <l>The quicke Infection: whether't be the Pact</l>
                  <l>Of Fate, and will of Heauen which doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Or Gods immediate angry mooued hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:180761:34"/>As 'tis; O pull it in, thou Gracious Power,</l>
                  <l>And let not this blind Enemie deuoure</l>
                  <l>The Grace of <hi>England.</hi> CHARLES implores, wee</l>
                  <l>With him in zealous Oriſons agree:</l>
                  <l>Heate him for vs, and vs for him; and ſtay</l>
                  <l>Thy dreadfull vengeance, which doth now diſplay</l>
                  <l>Horror through all thy People, and begins</l>
                  <l>To ſhew the vgly portraict of our ſins,</l>
                  <l>Which haue pull'd downe thy wrath. O let ſuffice</l>
                  <l>That world of bloud in foreine Ayre that lyes,</l>
                  <l>Of noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſoules, whoſe carkaſſes</l>
                  <l>The brutiſh Shores, wild Fields and greedy Seas</l>
                  <l>Expoſe to Dogs, to rauenous Fowles, and Fiſhes;</l>
                  <l>Ah, little anſwering to the tender wiſhes</l>
                  <l>Of their poore mothers, who at home the while</l>
                  <l>Gape at their childrens Honours, and beguile</l>
                  <l>Their early feares with too late hopes: alas</l>
                  <l>They little thinke, that now the ſoyled Graſſe</l>
                  <l>Vſurpes their deare embraces, and grim Fate</l>
                  <l>Sits pale vpon thoſe Beauties, which of late</l>
                  <l>They made their Ages comforts, who now ſhall</l>
                  <l>Ah! be bound to them for a Buriall.</l>
                  <l>O call to mind this Fatall Yeere, wherein</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Equally and iuſtly ſent.</note>Thy Iuſtice hath beene equall to our Sin;</l>
                  <l>Both great: O let thy bleſſed Goodneſſe ſtill,</l>
                  <l>As it is wont to doe, ſurpaſſe our Ill.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe men whom we did loue, whom we did truſt</l>
                  <l>Should be our Shields, are turn'd to Shades, to Duſt:</l>
                  <l>Let the in throned Soule of IAMES implore,</l>
                  <l>That after Him, thou puniſh His no more.</l>
                  <l>Let the great Spirit of OXFORD, which hath paſt</l>
                  <l>The Sentence of thy Anger, be the laſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:180761:34"/>Thou plagueſt vs withall; and let vs know,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill thou pittieſt vs, poore men, below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But neuer let this Land endure againe</l>
                  <l>That wofull ſolitude, which once did raigne</l>
                  <l>In our faire Cities; which, neglected left,</l>
                  <l>In a deplored ruine, ſhew'd the theft</l>
                  <l>Of angrie Fate: when ſcarce a tenant Mouſe</l>
                  <l>Was left, in many a faire vnpeopled houſe,</l>
                  <l>But the ſad Owles and Night Rauens aloofe,</l>
                  <l>Did keepe their Reuels on the ſilent roofe:</l>
                  <l>When at high Noone one paſſing by, ſhould meet</l>
                  <l>A Mid-night Darke, and ſilence in the ſtreet;</l>
                  <l>When in the wayes well-pau'd and worne before</l>
                  <l>By frequent ſteps of men, there now grew ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of vncouth Graſſe; and Harueſts now apace</l>
                  <l>Grew where they once were ſold, i'th'Market-place:</l>
                  <l>When as no Merryments, no Sports, no Playes</l>
                  <l>Were knowne at all, and yet all Holy-dayes.</l>
                  <l>No Papers then ouer the doores were ſet,</l>
                  <l>With, <hi>Chambers readie furniſh'd to be let;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But a ſad, <hi>Lord haue mercie vpon vs,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>A bloody <hi>Croſſe,</hi> as fatall Markes did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Able to fright one from the Prayer. The time</l>
                  <l>Then held it an inexpiable Crime,</l>
                  <l>To viſit a ſicke friend: Strange Stoure, wherein</l>
                  <l>Loue was a fault, and Charitie a ſin;</l>
                  <l>When Bad did feare infection from the Good,</l>
                  <l>And men did hate their cruell Neighbour-hood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twas a deplored time, wherein the Skyes</l>
                  <l>Themſelues did labour, and let fall their eyes;</l>
                  <l>When one might ſee the Sunne, with ſallow hayre</l>
                  <l>And languiſhing complexion, dull the ayre:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:180761:35"/>Looking eeu'n ſo, as when at <hi>Chryſes</hi> Plaint,</l>
                  <l>He went like Night, the <hi>Graecian</hi> troupes to taint</l>
                  <l>With ſad Infection; when his dire ſhafts caſt,</l>
                  <l>Kill'd more than <hi>Hector</hi> in the nine yeeres paſt.</l>
                  <l>The Heauens were cloath'd with bleak miſts, &amp; the aire,</l>
                  <l>With the thick Dampe, was ſtrucke into deſpaire</l>
                  <l>Of future cleareneſſe, or ſerener day,</l>
                  <l>But that the Clouds for feare ran oft away.</l>
                  <l>The Night, whoſe dewie ſhade had wont to tame</l>
                  <l>The ſoultry reliques of the Mid-day flame,</l>
                  <l>Diſtill'd no Chryſtall Pearles vpon the ground;</l>
                  <l>But wrapt in vaporous ſmoake, and cloath'd around</l>
                  <l>With poyſonous Exhalations, did affright</l>
                  <l>The trembling Moone; whoſe dim and paler light</l>
                  <l>Look'd with that countenance, as if againe</l>
                  <l>Her ſiluer hornes ſhould ne're eſcape the Wane,</l>
                  <l>So to renew her Circuit. The dull Quire</l>
                  <l>Of ſickly Starres ſhew'd now no ſmiling fire,</l>
                  <l>But ſhone like vn-ſnuff'd Tapers: as if Fate</l>
                  <l>Did giue them leaue now to prognoſticate</l>
                  <l>Their owne eſtate, not others; and applie</l>
                  <l>Themſelues at laſt to ſad Aſtrologie.</l>
                  <l>The poyſon-clutter'd Springs, with <hi>Plague</hi> infus'd,</l>
                  <l>Ran not with Chryſtall torrents, as they vs'd;</l>
                  <l>But in dull ſtreames, as them dire influence fills,</l>
                  <l>With fainting pace, ſcarce reach'd vnto their rills:</l>
                  <l>And languid Riuers, which before did paſſe</l>
                  <l>The Chryſtall with their cleareneſſe; now, alas,</l>
                  <l>Looke muddie, without ſtirring: and their ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>That wont to be all ſpangled with the beames</l>
                  <l>Of the blithe Sunne; now, in a weltring floud,</l>
                  <l>Ran not with water, but prodigious bloud.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:180761:35"/>Thoſe Trees whereof the Antients vs'd to raiſe</l>
                  <l>Their Funerall Piles, might in theſe fatall dayes</l>
                  <l>Burne at their owne Death's, which in ſad deſpaire</l>
                  <l>Spred not their leauie beauties through the ayre,</l>
                  <l>But ſuffer'd Autumne in the Spring: forlorne</l>
                  <l>And ferall Cypreſſe now had cauſe to mourne,</l>
                  <l>Poppeyes themſelues this time in death did ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>And the Myrrhe-tree had reaſon here to weepe</l>
                  <l>A funerall Perfume: thoſe gaudie flowers</l>
                  <l>Which wont to make Ghirlonds for Paramours,</l>
                  <l>Mourn'd in their drouping brauery, and ſpread</l>
                  <l>The ground at their owne deaths, as for the dead,</l>
                  <l>The Corne grew not, as if it meant t' undoo</l>
                  <l>Men not with <hi>Plague</hi> alone, but <hi>Famine</hi> too.</l>
                  <l>Herbs, Phyſicks Soueraignes, here infected die,</l>
                  <l>And for themſelues could finde no remedie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The brute Beaſts now, which Nature to beſtow</l>
                  <l>The Excellence on Man, did make with low</l>
                  <l>Downe-looking Poſtures, firſt did feele the rage</l>
                  <l>Of th' Earth-borne <hi>Plague,</hi> and died before their age.</l>
                  <l>The long-liu'd Hart this time to die began,</l>
                  <l>Before it reach'd vnto the age of Man.</l>
                  <l>The faithfull Spaniell, by his death, did trie</l>
                  <l>The miſchiefe of his well-nos'd Facultie,</l>
                  <l>And ranging with quicke Sent, did ſooneſt proue</l>
                  <l>Th'infectious Malice of the Dogge aboue.</l>
                  <l>The luſtie Steed, ſcouring in's Game apace,</l>
                  <l>Lights on Deaths Gole, in middle of his Race:</l>
                  <l>The nimble Fowle as th'ayre it flyes around,</l>
                  <l>Flags his ſick wings, and ſinkes vnto the ground,</l>
                  <l>Not long before to the remorſeleſſe Skie</l>
                  <l>In ſillie Notes haue ſung his Elegie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:180761:36"/>The luckleſſe Night-Rauens, which vs'd to grone</l>
                  <l>The death of others, now might Dirge their owne:</l>
                  <l>The Snow-plum'd Swan, as it did gently ride</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſiluer Streame, ſung forth, and di'de.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Anon the Damp dares breake into the Walls,</l>
                  <l>Making a way by thouſand Funerals:</l>
                  <l>Who can expreſſe th'aſtoniſhment and feare,</l>
                  <l>Which doth at entrance of a <hi>Plague</hi> appeare?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Euen ſo the fleeced Heard doth tremble, when</l>
                  <l>An Aburne Lyon, hungry from his Den,</l>
                  <l>Breakes in among 'em: then you may behold</l>
                  <l>The pale-look'd Shepheard gaze vpon his Fold</l>
                  <l>With helpeleſſe pitie, the poore Lam-kins creepe</l>
                  <l>Vnder their Dams; the ſillie trembling Sheepe</l>
                  <l>Stand full of cold amazement at the ſight,</l>
                  <l>Small hope for mercy, and leſſe hope in flight.</l>
                  <l>Expecting onely which of all ſhall ſcape.</l>
                  <l>The readie horror of the Lyons rape.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Other Diſeaſes warning giue before,</l>
                  <l>That we may reckon, and acquit the Score</l>
                  <l>Of our ſinnes Prodigalitie: in this,</l>
                  <l>We ſcarce can be reſolued whether 'tis</l>
                  <l>Sickneſſe, or Death it ſelfe; ſo quicke it tries</l>
                  <l>The ſtrength of Nature, ſo ſoone poore Man dies:</l>
                  <l>That many to repoſe in th' Euening lying,</l>
                  <l>Haue made their ſleepe true kin to Death, by dying</l>
                  <l>Before the Morne. Ah! who would then deferre</l>
                  <l>A preparation for this Meſſenger</l>
                  <l>Of bleſs'd or curs'd Eternitie? What man</l>
                  <l>Would ſtill preſume to ſinne, that knowes the ſpan</l>
                  <l>Of ſhort vncertaine Life? Yee gracious Powers,</l>
                  <l>That meaſure out the minutes and the houres</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:180761:36"/>Of this our wandring Pilgrimage, reſtraine</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſodaine ſlaughter-men; or, good God waine</l>
                  <l>Vs from our ſinnes, that wee may neither feare</l>
                  <l>The rape of Death, nor couet to be here:</l>
                  <l>O curbe this raging Sickneſſe, which with ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Bereaues vs of the meanes of Penitence.</l>
                  <l>When a dire Phrenſie ſeizeth on the Braine,</l>
                  <l>Full of reſiſtleſſe flame, and full of paine;</l>
                  <l>That Madneſſe, which no cure can well appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Is but a Symptome, vnto this Diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>Our bloud all fire, as if it did portend</l>
                  <l>We were not here to ſtay, but ſoone aſcend;</l>
                  <l>When ſtreames of ſulphur through our veins do glide,</l>
                  <l>And ſcarce the ſenſe of ſorrow doth abide.</l>
                  <l>This time how miſerable, may we gueſſe,</l>
                  <l>Where want of ſenſe, is chiefeſt happineſſe:</l>
                  <l>When the diſtracted Soule can ſcarce deuiſe</l>
                  <l>How to ſupply the weakeſt Faculties</l>
                  <l>Of the diſturbed Body; but preſents</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Eye ſtrange obiects, ſtrange portents,</l>
                  <l>And antique ſhadowes: when the feueriſh rage</l>
                  <l>Sets vs on Iourneyes oft, and Pilgrimage,</l>
                  <l>And entertaines our wild and wandring ſight</l>
                  <l>With monſtrous Land-ſchips, able to affright</l>
                  <l>A man in's wits: when the deceiued Eares</l>
                  <l>Doe apprehend what ere the Fancie feares;</l>
                  <l>The grones of Ghoſts, and whiſpering of Sprites,</l>
                  <l>The ſilken tread of Faeries in the Nights,</l>
                  <l>The language of an ayrie Picture, howles</l>
                  <l>Of funerall Dogs, and warnings of ſad Owles.</l>
                  <l>The Taſt diſtaſteth all things, and the ſame</l>
                  <l>Is ſweet, and bitter, when the inward flame</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:180761:37"/>Furres the ſwolne tongue; &amp; the quick Feeling marr'd.</l>
                  <l>Knoweth no difference betweene ſoft and hard:</l>
                  <l>Such a confuſed Error doth diſtract</l>
                  <l>The labouring ſenſes, ſo is the Fancie rackt</l>
                  <l>By the dire ſickneſſe; when from place to place</l>
                  <l>The Bodie rolleth, and would faine embrace</l>
                  <l>Some Icie cooler: but alas, the heat</l>
                  <l>Aſſwaging, there enſues a Marble ſweat</l>
                  <l>'Twixt Death and Nature, wreſtling: then appeare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe deadly Characters, which th'Enſigne beare</l>
                  <l>Before approching Fate; which notice giue,</l>
                  <l>None <hi>ſpotleſſe</hi> die, how euer they did liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſickneſſe comfortleſſe; when we doe feare</l>
                  <l>To ſee thoſe friends whom we doe loue moſt deare.</l>
                  <l>The Miniſters Deuotion here doth ſticke,</l>
                  <l>By leauing Viſitation of the ſicke,</l>
                  <l>Making the Seruice Booke imperfect: when</l>
                  <l>We ſee a croſſed Doore, as 'twere a Den</l>
                  <l>Of Serpents, or a Prodigie, we ſhun</l>
                  <l>The poore diſtreſſed Habitation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Death as comfortleſſe; where not appeares</l>
                  <l>One friend, to ſhed ſome tender funerall teares:</l>
                  <l>Blacke Night's the onely Mourner: No ſad Verſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſolemne flowers doe decke the drearie Herſe:</l>
                  <l>Some few old folke perhaps, for many a yeere</l>
                  <l>Who haue forgot to weepe, attend the Beere;</l>
                  <l>Such, whoſe dry age hath made moſt fit to keepe</l>
                  <l>Th'infected without feare, but not to weepe;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe kin to death, made them not feare to die,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe deafeneſſe made them then fit companie</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ſicke, when they were ſpeechleſſe growne:</l>
                  <l>A miſerable Conſolation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:180761:37"/>But had you look'd about, you might haue ſeene</l>
                  <l>Death in each corner, and the ſecret teene</l>
                  <l>Of angry Deſtiny: No ſport diſpels</l>
                  <l>The miſts of ſorrow; a ſad ſilence dwels</l>
                  <l>In all the ſtreets, and a pale terrour ſeizes</l>
                  <l>Vpon their faces, who had no Diſeaſes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So vſuall 'twas, before the morne to dye,</l>
                  <l>That when at Night two friends left company,</l>
                  <l>They would not ſay, <hi>Good Night;</hi> but thus alone</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God ſend's a ioyfull Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If two or three daies interpos'd betweene,</l>
                  <l>One friend by chance another friend had ſeene,</l>
                  <l>It was as ſtrange, and ioyfull, as to ſome,</l>
                  <l>When a deare friend doth from the <hi>Indies</hi> come.</l>
                  <l>Throgh the nak'd town, of death there was ſuch plenty,</l>
                  <l>One Bell at once was faine to ring for twenty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No Clocks were heard to ſtrike vpon their Bels,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe nothing rung but death-lamenting Knels.</l>
                  <l>Strange, that the Houres ſhould faile to tell the Day,</l>
                  <l>When time to thouſands ran ſo faſt away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Time was confus'd, and kept at ſuch a plight,</l>
                  <l>The Day to thouſands now was made a Night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hundreds that neuer ſaw before, but di'de,</l>
                  <l>At one ſame time, in one ſame Graue abide;</l>
                  <l>That our weake Fancies, if we did not hold</l>
                  <l>It Profanation, here to be too bold,</l>
                  <l>Might wonder what, being ſtrangers, they would ſay</l>
                  <l>To one another at the Iudgement Day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some, by their feare to goe to Church debarr'd,</l>
                  <l>Anon are carryed dead vnto the Yard.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Church-yards gron'd, with too much death oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And the Earth reſts not, 'cauſe ſo many reſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:180761:38"/>And Churches now with too much buriall fed,</l>
                  <l>Fear'd they ſhould haue no meeting but of Dead:</l>
                  <l>Death fell on death, and men began to feare</l>
                  <l>That men would want to carry forth the Beere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Bearers, Keepers, Sextons that remaine</l>
                  <l>Surpaſſe in number all the towne againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Friends here kill'd friends, womb-fellowes kill their Brothers</l>
                  <l>Fathers their Sons, and Daughters kill their Mothers:</l>
                  <l>By one another (ſtrange!) ſo many di'de</l>
                  <l>And yet no murder here, no Homicide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Mother great with Childe by the Plagues might</l>
                  <l>Infects to death her childe not borne to light.</l>
                  <l>So killing that which yet ne're liu'd; the wombe</l>
                  <l>Of th'aliue Mother, to th'dead Childe was tombe,</l>
                  <l>Where in the fleſhy graue the ſtill Babe lying,</l>
                  <l>Doth kill his mother by his owne firſt dying.</l>
                  <l>Her trauaile here on Earth ſhe could not tend</l>
                  <l>But finiſhes in heauen her Iournies end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To others, frolicke ſet vnto their meales,</l>
                  <l>Secure of Death, ſlie Death vpon them ſteales,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrikes among 'em, ſo that thence in ſpeed</l>
                  <l>With heauy Cheere th'are borne the wormes to feed.</l>
                  <l>To ſome at worke, to others at their play,</l>
                  <l>To thouſands death makes a long Holy-day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death all conditions equally inuades,</l>
                  <l>Nor riches, power, nor beauty here perſwades,</l>
                  <l>Old dye with young, with women men, the rage</l>
                  <l>Of the dire Plague ſpares neither ſex nor age.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt powerfull Influence of ruling Starres</l>
                  <l>Which with blinde darts kill more than bloudy Wars,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180761:38"/>Reſiſtleſſe Famine, greedy time, or when</l>
                  <l>The threatfull hand of tyrants ſtriketh men</l>
                  <l>Into pale terrour, more than all diſeaſes,</l>
                  <l>Ah, happy he who heauen leaſt diſpleaſes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180761:39"/>
            <head>Some principall Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Colledge of bodily Phyſicians, and <hi>Galen</hi> Prince of them, their preſcript in time of Plague. <hi>Page 1:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rules for fleeing or departing in time of Plague. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The yeeres <hi>1603</hi> and <hi>1625.</hi> alleadged. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Romaniſts and their S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> confuted. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their execrable and blaſphemous deuotion and ſuperſtition in Plague-time confuted. <hi>p. 15. &amp; 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alleadged for prayer. <hi>p. 7. &amp; 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whereunto <hi>Dauid</hi> and his family fled in Plague-time. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obiections againſt moderate fleeing in time of Plague, anſwered. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beza</hi> alleadged for lawfulneſſe of fleeing: <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Touching the Magiſtrate and Miniſters fleeing. <hi>p. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> concerning prayer. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dauids</hi> Conſcience, Humility, Memory, Wiſedome in Plague-time and other affliction. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Famine, Wars, and Peſtilence Gods Trinitie of puniſhments. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> alleadged for prayer. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> his anſwere to a Widow, and her memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reply to him. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bowing the bodily knee to Angels forbidden. <hi>p. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hilary</hi> cited againſt the Papiſts. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> cited for <hi>Locris</hi> and <hi>Crotone,</hi> that neuer were infected with the Plague. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Comfort for a weake Conſcience of a conſcious ſinner viſited with the Plague. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>King <hi>Dauids</hi> Phyſician in time of Plague. <hi>p. 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180761:40"/>In time of Plague or any other affliction, we muſt pray for others as well as our ſelues. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Faith in prayer like a beautifull Queene. <hi>p. 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> cited for Faith in prayer. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> cited for confidence in asking. <hi>p. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meere vocall, verball, and formall prayers, likened to the Prince of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Aſcanius</hi> their Parrats, the one rehearſing the <hi>Pater-noſter,</hi> the other the <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>Aſcanius</hi> his deuotion like to his Parrats. <hi>p. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gods will holy, iuſt, equitable, not like earthly Princes. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The high commendation of faithfull prayer. <hi>p. 37. 38. 39 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Londoners</hi> laudable Exerciſe. <hi>p. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
